<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Maschil vnmasked In a treatise defending this sentence of our Church: vidz. the present Romish Church hath not the nature of the true Church. Against the publick opposition of Mr. Cholmley, and Mr. Butterfield, two children revolted in opinion from their owne subscription, and the faith of their mother the Church of England. By Thomas Spencer.</title>
            <author>Spencer, Thomas, fl. 1628-1629.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1629</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 203 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 62 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12768</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23073</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117745</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852955</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852955</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18310</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12768)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18310)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 976:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Maschil vnmasked In a treatise defending this sentence of our Church: vidz. the present Romish Church hath not the nature of the true Church. Against the publick opposition of Mr. Cholmley, and Mr. Butterfield, two children revolted in opinion from their owne subscription, and the faith of their mother the Church of England. By Thomas Spencer.</title>
                  <author>Spencer, Thomas, fl. 1628-1629.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28], 95, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Iones, dwelling in Red-crosse-streete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1629]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to "The state of the now-Romane Church" by Hugh Cholmley and "Maschil" by Robert Butterfield.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cholmley, Hugh, ca. 1574-1641. --  State of the now-Romane Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Butterfield, Robert. --  Maschil --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18310:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18310:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MASCHIL VNMASKED. <hi>JN</hi> A TREATISE DEFENDING this ſentence of our Church: <hi>Vidz. The preſent Romiſh Church hath not the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the true Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againſt the publick oppoſition of Mr. <hi>Cholmley,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Butterfield,</hi> two children revolted in opinion from their owne ſubſcription, and the faith of their Mother the Church of ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>BY THOMAS SPENCER.</p>
            <q>Who is this that darkeneth Counſell by words with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out knowledge. <bibl>
                  <hi>Iob. 38.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>My wrath is kindled againſt thee and thy two friends, for you haue not ſpoken of mee the thing that is right. <bibl>
                  <hi>Iob. 42.7.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by WILLIAM IONES, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in <hi>Red-croſſe-ſtreete.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18310:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18310:2"/>
            <head>TO THE COMMONS HOVSE OF <hi>PARLIAMENT.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt graue, and honourable Senate:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen children are preſſed with the want of good,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> or feare of ill, they reſort vnto their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents. This is our preſent caſe. The ſute which wee preſent vnto your graue iudgements, and Paternall care, is no leſſe then a matter of Religion and State. For ſo it is, that two revolted children of this our Engliſh Church and Common-wealth, are riſen vp in hoſtile manner a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Mother.</p>
            <p>She hath decreed (even in ſo many words) that,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <q>The Romiſh Church, is ſo farre wide from the nature of the true Church, as nothing can be more.</q>
            </p>
            <p>They vndertake to maintaine, that,
<q>The preſent Romiſh Church, hath the true, and formall eſſence of a Church.</q>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18310:3"/>
            <p>This then is our requeſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> that, your Wiſedomes will be pleaſed to take this deed of theirs into your father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſideration, and to procure ſuch redreſſe therein, as ſtandeth with your place, and power: Herein wee doubt not to be heard; becauſe, (according to the law of God, and inſtinct of nature) Fathers <hi>lay vp for their Children,</hi> and moſt willingly expend their ſtore vpon them, when need requires. Our confidence herein is the more increaſed, by two reaſons; to wit, Our perpetuall experience of your willing, &amp; ready providence for this our Church &amp; Common-wealth, &amp; the greatneſſe of the matter wherein we are your humble Petitioners.</p>
            <p>If our Church had ſaid nothing,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> or ſpake doubtfully of the point, then we had not put it to their account as a fault, becauſe, in all ages, and in the preſent Romiſh Church ſuch Divinity diſputations haue beene and are allowed: And there is good reaſon for it, for thereby the trueth (in all doubtfull things at laſt) hath beene cleerd: and hath had the victory in the end: and, for this very cauſe, the preſent Romiſh Church doth voluntarily, (&amp; of choiſe) giue leaue to their ſchooles, to diſpute the points of the concurrence of actuall grace, and mans will in every ſupernaturall action. And of the kinde of worſhip to be given to the Images of Chriſt, the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and the Saints: becauſe, it now appeares, that the words of the <hi>Trent</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, touching them both, are doubtfull and ambigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18310:3"/>
            <p>But this is not our caſe;
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> our Church hath delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red her Judgement in a ſingle Propoſition, conſiſting of termes wherein there can be no doubt, or queſtion; and the attribution is vniuerſall, and without limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: ſo as, no reaſonable man can make a queſtion of her meaning. Now (beholde) ſhe hath not reſted con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with this, (which indeede is enough) but, (to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the ignorant obſtinacy of all Opponents) ſhe hath declared, by a compariſon of equallity, the extent and amplitude of her predication: and ſaith, <hi>The Church of Rome is ſo farre wide from the nature of the true Church, as nothing can be more.</hi> Whereby we vnderſtand, that, ſhee conceiues the preſent Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church to bee wholly deſtitute of <hi>every (the leaſt) jot or tittle of</hi> the nature, and eſſence of the true Church: for ſo it is with every Society, which is ſo farre wide from the nature of the true Church, as nothing can bee more.</p>
            <p>Now, what title ſhall we giue to this deed?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> vnder what head ſhall hee ranke this offence? what puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or degree of puniſhment doe they deſerue? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is not within the power of my vnderſtanding, nor in the nature of my place, and condition, (finally) to determine: vnto you, and to your moſt deepe and profound Iudgement, muſt I appeale for that: Yet I humbly craue leaue to ſhew my opinion, leſt I ſeeme cauſleſly to complaine.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18310:4"/>
            <p>The deed of theſe men,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> can deſerue no leſſe then to be branded with the name of contention: for, from a <hi>roote of bitterneſſe,</hi> and the ſpirit of contention, it did originally grow and ariſe; J ſay it ſprang from hence: becauſe the tree and all the branches thereof, ſavours of ſuch a root, and cannot be conceiv'd to grow from other ſoile. Contention it is, and nothing elſe: becauſe it oppoſeth things ordeined, and ſetled ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and with great authority, and ſo continued for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares together, no man daring publickly, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly to ſay againſt it. But, which is moſt of all, ſubſcribed it is, as the faith of our Church, by theſe very Opponents. Yea, a high degree of contention it muſt be accounted becauſe, the minde from whence it did flow, ſeemes altogether vnquiet, and reſtleſſe. Who would not content himſelfe with that faith that is thus eſtabliſhed. I ſay <hi>thus,</hi> becauſe the parties that collected it, vſed all poſsible diligence, and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: they were learned, and of exceeding gravity, and ſtaydneſſe: all ages (with vs) haue agreed vnto their iudgements: yea, even theſe Opponents haue had their ſhare in it, and not in words, onely, that paſſe away: but vnder their owne hand writing, that remaines for ever. Can the gainſaying of things thus adorned, and commended to theſe Opponents, proceed from any ground but the ſpirit that can finde no place to reſt in? Surely no: and J preſume, that every ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed man will ſay ſo with me.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18310:4"/>
            <p>Theſe Opponents doe tell vs,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> (and we muſt ſay ſo too, if wee will beleeue them) that, <hi>It is charity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Romiſh Church</hi> that hatched this deed: but we muſt not truſt them, the father and the childe are ſo vnlike. What does charity bid them hate their friend? Loues he indeed, that pulleth out his Mothers heart to giue life to her vowed foe? Theſe Opponents may ſay ſo: becauſe this their deed ſorts with it, but, he that hath his eyes in his head, will reckon them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt that number, who <hi>caſteth about firebrands, and deadly things, and ſaith I am in jeſt,</hi> Prov. <hi>26.19.</hi> Jf then their charity was vnfeigned, they would loue their Mother firſt, and others after, and in relation vnto her: ſeeing then, theſe Opponents doe not ſo, but the contrary, we muſt conclude, not their charity, but, their contention, formed this deed.</p>
            <p>This deed can be no leſſe a ſinne againſt God,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> and I thinke others will ſay ſo with me: though I giue no other reaſon for it, but the odious account which the Apoſtle makes of ſuch as are contentious. <hi>1 Cor. 11.16.</hi> An offence it is againſt our State; becauſe, the continuance in things well ordered is a fundamentall law, in every Common-wealth. So is it an offence hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous and grievous: for he that ſevers and pul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the limbes of the body, deſtroyes the perſon, and he that doth ſo, muſt be reckoned a maine and principall deſtroyer thereof; and thus doe theſe Opponents: the
<pb facs="tcp:18310:5"/>life of our Church, and all the members thereof is made, and vnited together, into one body by the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of her faith: he then, that, overthrowes, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyes thoſe Articles; diſcipates, and haleth in peeces her whole body, and being: and thus doe theſe Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents in their deed in queſtion.</p>
            <p>Puniſhment is due vnto them,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> &amp; ſo much (J hope) J may ſay without offence, vnto your high, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable authority: becauſe, the thing it ſelfe is ſo apparent. Very reaſon it ſelfe doth tell vs, <hi>The ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of every being that is good, makes guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of puniſhment.</hi> Now the deed in queſtion being a ſubverſion of the faith of our Church of <hi>England,</hi> by the ſame rule, muſt needs likewiſe make ſo guilty. The degree of this puniſhment, J dare not name, J may not thinke vpon, ſeeing the cauſe now in hand is preſented before your ſacred Tribunall, whoſe office it is to diſcerne, determine, and adiudge the ſame. Yet (with all ſubmiſsion) J craue a word or two of that matter. If any vnder the command of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſhould oppoſe the very words of the <hi>Trent</hi> Councell, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally where the thing is decreed explorately, ſo as no queſtion can bee made of her ſenſe &amp; meaning; ſuch a one, J ſay, ſhould bee held worthy of no ſmall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, and we certainly know it, becauſe ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are pronounced <hi>accurſed</hi> by that Councell; &amp; purſued with fire, and all extremity, as perpetuall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience
<pb facs="tcp:18310:5"/>doth ſhew. If theſe Opponents lived in that Church, &amp; ſhould defend this ſentence, <hi>[The office of judging the ſenſe &amp; meaning of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures belongs not to the Church]</hi> we might ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily gueſſe at their puniſhment. Jf then) hat Church eſteemeth ſuch oppoſition vnto her faith to demerit ſo highly, how can we eſteeme to deſerue but little, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what their faith is to them, the ſame our faith is to vs: but with this difference, their faith is erroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſo is not ours; as the enſuing diſcourſe will evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſhew: how much (then an oppoſition to an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronious faith is leſſe hurtfull, then an oppoſition to a true faith, ſo much more puniſhment doto be deſerue, that oppoſeth ours, more then he that oppoſeth theirs: &amp; thus much is all wherewith I will trouble you tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the deed in queſtion.</p>
            <p>Now, J hope J may alſo without reproofe,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> ſhew ſome other reaſon whereupon to moue you. If this deed be let paſſe without controle, ſee what will follow. <hi>1.</hi> Our enemies of the Romiſh Church will triumph over vs, and thus they will argue: With you is not the true Church, for where that is, there is vnity, and a meanes of vnity in all matters of faith: but theſe are not with you: for ſee, your Church beleeveth that the Romiſh Church hath not the nature of the true Church, yet two of yours, yea &amp; after their ſubſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, doe out face her with the contradictory, &amp; carry
<pb facs="tcp:18310:6"/>it away when they haue done, no man ſayes black is their eye. <hi>2.</hi> The ſalvation of the vnſtable, &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe will be really hindred: ſuch a man will ſay vnto our Church; if you taught mee the way to life, doubtleſſe you would agree in it, or ſuppreſſe the gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers: ſeeing therefore you doe neither the one, nor the other; wee muſt conclude, that the way to life is not with you, &amp; conſequently it is no where, for in your iudgement, the Romiſh Church hath it not; or (at leaſt) men of good parts might ſay; if you agree not vpon the way to heaven, then 'tis hopeleſſe for vs to finde it; becauſe, with you are the aged in yeeres, great in experience, abundant in learning, conſiderate in reſolving, &amp; in the office of governing: if our hopes to finde heaven be vaine, &amp; idle, why ſhall we beſtow our paines that wayes? who would labour without pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit? who would lay out his ſilver to fill his belly with the Eaſt winde? Surely no man: wherefore here is our reſt, ſeeing there is no profit in the ſervice of God, we will determine with our ſelves &amp; ſay, <hi>We care not for the knowledge of the moſt high, let vs caſt his lawes behind our back; let vs eate, and drink, for to morrow wee ſhall die. 3.</hi> The glory of our Church (at leaſt) is abated, nay, I may truly ſay, her beauty is ſtayned with an eye-ſore, too vgly to be looked vpon. He that caſteth dirt in his Mothers face, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in nothing is wanting for feature, or complexion, ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:18310:6"/>haue little thankes for his labour: what then ſhall bee bee accounted, that ſcratcheth her, till ſhee bleedes? Nay more, that pulleth off, &amp; treadeth vnder foote, all the ornaments of her countenance? If our Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents gaue the lye to a man of honeſt reputation, hee ſhould diſgrace him not a little; but if hee charged him with that lye, to the loſſe of his credit for ever, we know he ſhould burt him finally, &amp; for ever. But thus (J ſay) if no better then on this manner, deale theſe Opponents with their Mother the Church of <hi>England:</hi> ſhee hath determined what muſt bee held in certaine points of religion, &amp; in that her counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance exceeds in beauty; becauſe ſhe did ſo determine, for the avoiding of contention, and ſetling of Peace: <hi>Peace, (yea Peace)</hi> that viſage of Peace, the moſt louely, delightfull, and acceptable countenance, of all countenances: yet beholde, &amp; ceaſe not to wonder, our two Opponents will not keepe this peace, they haue broken downe the walls of that fortreſſe, what ſhee intended for vnity, &amp; concord they divert to fracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and diſcord, &amp; ſo haue robbed her, of her goodly, &amp; beautious feature, &amp; complexion. Nay, which is more, they haue given her that lye, which will ſtick to her ribbs for ever, without the exemplary puniſhment of theſe offendours: for, if she be falſe in her greateſt children, for learning, gravity, wiſedome, &amp; piety, all met together, when they gaue that witneſſe; then
<pb facs="tcp:18310:7"/>who will truſt her? for, if her word can be true at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time, it would be true then. Now, thoſe, &amp; each one of them, are ſo inconvenient that, J conceiue, they muſt be eſteem'd ſo intollerable, if that be ſo, wee haue good reaſon to bemoane our ſelues vnto you, &amp; ſeeke for redreſſe at your hands.</p>
            <p>Can wee imagine,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> that, our Church and the ſoules of her children, onely, shall bee loſers by this deed in queſtion? Surely no man can bee ſo much miſtaken: for marke, if they ſcape with this deed, who will not thus argue? If Oppoſers in matters of faith bee not reck ned offedours, then Oppoſers in matters of State muſt be held innocent, ſeeing the firſt is of more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous conſequence then the ſecond. If wee may op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the State, who vvill obey? ſeeing liberty is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fancied then ſubiection, Jf vvee are freed from obedience, then farevvell government: ſeeing, to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne, &amp; to obey, are ſuch relatiues as doe ſtand, &amp; fall together. If then, governing &amp; obeying be taken avvay, all things come to confuſion. As then vvee vvill a void deſtruction to our Church, &amp; Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvealth, ſo muſt vve open our ſelues before you, &amp; eraue your aſsiſtance.</p>
            <p>Hither to I haue opened our cauſe,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> &amp; the reaſon of our requeſt, it remaineth, (as ſome men vvould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue) that I moue you alſo to the manner vvherein to proceed in the cauſe: but, I altogether decline that,
<pb facs="tcp:18310:7"/>ſuch aſſurance haue I of the abundant wiſdome iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, learning, &amp; providence vvhich dvvelleth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, that in my ſelfe I bluſh to thinke of that deed. Some perhaps would incourage mee to provoke you to redreſſe this evill by force of Argument, but that pleaſeth me as little: becauſe I know the trueth of God remaineth with you, &amp; therewithall the loue of the trueth; ſo as, you cannot be negligent in this buſineſſe: ſeeing the loue of the trueth cauſeth ſuch as haue it, to doe nothing againſt the trueth, but for it, I am aſſured, the voice of Chriſt when he comes to Iudge the world, does perpetually ſound in your eares; even as if by liuely &amp; perſonall voice, you heard him ſay: <hi>Thou good Steward, and faithfull, thou haſt beene faithfull in a little, I will make thee Ruler over much, enter into your Maſters joy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shall I tell you, no hindrance lyeth in your way,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> that may diſcourage you from this worke? No, no: that is altogether needleſſe. Wherefore J haue no more to ſay, but (in the words of God himſelfe:) <hi>Goe on in this thy ſtrength, thou mighty man: for God is with you.</hi> And we, for our parts, doe liue in a ioyfull expectation, of a good, &amp; a happy iſſue, becauſe we know, <hi>God is the authour of trueth, and his eye lids preſerue pure knowledge, at whoſe ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing all his enemies,</hi> (even the maintainers of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour) <hi>ſhall be ſcattered:</hi> And you moſt graue &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:18310:8"/>honourable Senatours are worthy, watchfull, &amp; provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent inſtruments vnto his ſacred Maieſty our dread Soveraigne, in procuring the welfare of all the true members of this our Engliſh Church &amp; Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, among which members I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>To your Worthineſſe an humble ſuppliant, not the leaſt devoted: THOMAS SPENCER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:18310:8"/>
            <head>A PREFACE TO THE FOLLOWING DISCOVRSE, anſwering vnto ſome points, which <hi>concerne the matter in Common.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> I am compelled to make a Preface to the following diſputation, by a double law. The one is, perpetuall cuſtome vſed in this caſe, from which I may not vary; the other is, the matter it ſelfe: ſome things (in our preſent Opponents) are tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and belong vnto the whole matter, in ſuch an vniverſe, and common manner, that I could not anſwere them in any one particular paſſage: yet, it behooved me to giue thee ſatisfaction in them.</p>
            <p>Our preſent Opponents doe ſeeme to triumph,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> as if the cauſe in queſtion were cleerly theirs, ſo as, even we our ſelves at the firſt ſight might ſeeme vnreaſonable, if we thought not ſo too.</p>
            <p>They leade vs with huge mountaines of contumelious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, and in concluſion,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> they eſteem vs no better then to be <hi>Either laught, out or deſpiſed:</hi> So as, they account <hi>Their depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and defence, a thing condiſcended vnto in courteſie:</hi> for themſelues they haue another note, <hi>Inſtructers</hi> they are, and their Treatiſes are <hi>to giue Inſtruction.</hi> If you will know the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why, they tell vs alſo: In them, <hi>There is a spirit, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration of the Almighty giveth them vnderſtanding.</hi> Wherefore, they dare and doe provoke, even <hi>Cato himſelfe, to come in, and ſee, and cenſure, what they haue written and done.</hi> If you deſire to know why they challenge to themſelues theſe high preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, as belonging onely vnto them, they will not let you bee ignorant. <hi>Great men</hi> (ſay they) <hi>are not alwayes wiſe, neither doe
<pb facs="tcp:18310:9"/>the aged vnderstand Iudgement, therefore I ſaid, bearken to mee.</hi> Which reaſon is vtterly naught, vnleſſe all are fooles but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
            <p>Wiſe men doe vſe both their eares,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and I hope thou wilt doe ſo too, eſpecially in a cauſe of this high nature, and conſequence. If thou wilt doe ſo indeed, I dare aſſure thee, that, thou ſhalt finde, that they haue not vttered one true word, to their profit, or our hurt: for the matter it ſelfe, I muſt referre thee to the body of the diſputation, for things common thereunto, I will in this Preface performe my promiſe: and I will begin with the matter that concernes our ſelues.</p>
            <p>We defend the faith of our Church,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> ſubſcribed vnto by all ours, yea, even by theſe our preſent Opponents, and will they <hi>laugh vs out, and aeſpiſe vs for that?</hi> Is it their curteſie to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te, and defend themſelues againſt her.</hi> We propound the queſtion in her termes, and in a ſingle, ſimple or categoricall Propoſition. We explicate the termes of that queſtion, in the words wherein our Church hath done it before vs, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe our Opponents doe conſent and agree. We conclude that queſtion, in the ſame full ſyllogiſme wherein our Church hath concluded it, and not varied, come ſhort, or exceeded any one of her words. We further proue every part of that Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that is, or may be queſtioned; by the expreſſe word of God, or by a neceſſary application of the expreſſe word of God. We defend that Argument of hers, againſt all oppoſers: and finally, we reduce every Argument brought againſt her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to true forme, and ſhew what part we deny, and giue the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſuch deniall, and that in true forme of art: and muſt we needs be <hi>laught out, and deſpiſed for t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>?</hi> If they ſay, wee muſt be laughed out, and deſpiſed for any thing, it muſt be for theſe: for herin conſiſteth our greateſt folly. If they will haue vs laughed out for theſe, then I leaue thee good Reader to be Iudge betweene vs: if thou wilt ſay he is a foole that does thus, <hi>Theirs be the day</hi> for this time, becauſe we now want fit opportunity to defend our ſelues againſt them.</p>
            <p>All this while,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> we haue concealed the maine matter which they bring againſt vs, <hi>We write divirity without rethorick, and that is (in vs) either madnes, or impudency,</hi> But whether will
<pb facs="tcp:18310:9"/>they <hi>laugh vs out, or diſpoſe vs for this,</hi> wee know not their mind as yet. Is our ſtile horrid, and harſh, <hi>Is it not quaint, and neate enough for our Opponents pallet? Can we not delight their eares with iiggs, and tricks of wit? Surely then, we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be laughed out or deſpiſed</hi> by our Opponents: for that's their owne caſe, the one confeſſeth his ſtile to be ſuch, and the ſtile of the other is ſo indeed. Moreouer theſe Opponents and our ſelues may ioy ſo to be vſed; becauſe, all the ſchoole-men that haue liued in the world ioyne with vs, and goe hand in hand with vs the buſines.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We deale againſt perſons better then our ſelues:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> and therefore we want maners, and conſequently we must be laughed out, and deſpiſed for that.</hi> But is this true? Doe we oppoſe our ſelues to mens perſons, or qualities and condition; Nothing leſſe: the queſtion on foote is an Article of faith. A point in Divinity wherein the divine authority rules the caſe; the perſons, and conditions of man can beare no ſway, nor be admitted any roome, or place, but for this time let the perſons of men come in, and their qualities, honours, and conditions whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Yet we deale not againſt our betters, for (to ſay the leaſt) we are in the roome and behalfe of our Church, which wee dare preferre before all her Opponents, for they haue ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed vnto her, and thereby they haue acknowledged and done homage vnto her Lordſhip, and Dominion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wee quarrell the perſons of men in enuy to their aduancement and honours: becauſe he that ſaid thus now, ſaid ſo long,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten before, with the approbation of our whole Church repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, and without blame of them that doo now accuſe him.</hi> But is this true? our Opponents ſay ſo; but their proofe is inſuſfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, becauſe in it ſelfe 'tis vntrue, and nought in the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, perhaps their party avouched thus much before, and yet not ſeene, or not regarded: for, who would ſuſpect or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubt ſuch a friend as he ſeemed, and was accounted? If we were glaſiers, or the ſonnes of a glaſier, perhaps he might ſee our ſecret thoughts and intentions: but, becauſe we are not, we muſt not be <hi>laughed out, nor a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſed;</hi> becauſe we oppoſe not vnto any mans honour, and adnancement.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We caſt a ſtone that hitteth our Mother.</hi> If that be ſo: if wee
<pb facs="tcp:18310:10"/>haue done it, and ſtill avow the deed; let vs be <hi>laughed out or deſpiſed,</hi> chooſe them whether; but this is impoſſible, wee caſt no ſtones at all: by our office we hold vp our Buckler to defend our Mother, and to beare of ſuch ſtones as are caſt by others, if any ſtone hits our Mother, it is that which is caſt at the Church of Rome, for that is the thing in queſtion. If that ſtone hit our Mother, theſe Opponents muſt <hi>laugh her out or diſpiſe</hi> her for her labour; for 'tis ſhee that caſt it, we doe no more but iuſtifie her caſting. If theſe Opponents will <hi>laugh her out, or diſpiſe her</hi> let them do ſo to vs alſo, for good reaſon the Mother, &amp; Child ſhould ſhare alike, &amp; ſtand or fall together.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We cauſe our Church to ſuffer,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> becauſe we father a ſtrange and vntrue tenant vpon her.</hi> Now we know we ſhall not be <hi>laughed out; nor diſpiſed;</hi> for this: becauſe we ſay of her no more, no not one word leſſe, or more then ſhe hath ſaid vnto vs. If thus to impoſe deſerues <hi>laughter and diſpite,</hi> then to deny her to ſay what indeed ſhe hath ſaid deſerues <hi>laughter and diſpite;</hi> for the caſe is the ſame in both. It that be ſo, then our preſent Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents muſt be <hi>laughed out, and diſpiſed;</hi> for they deny her to ſay, what ſhe hath ſaid, &amp; ſo much the more they deſerve to bee <hi>laughed out, and diſpiſed;</hi> becauſe, they deny the thing wherein ſence it ſelfe (even their owne eyes) doth avow, and cannot be deceived, thus far touching the thing which concernes our ſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>They meane not to ſpeake a word in behalfe of the impure Church of Rome:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> but rather, if it were not done already they would vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer her nakedneſſe, and abhomination.</hi> And we are content to admit their pretence; becauſe, ſuch deepe proteſtations, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious cravings goes with it; but notwithſtanding they gaine nothing, for two reaſons, 1. becauſe, their deed cries loud, and inforceth ſtrongly to bring vs backe againe to Rome. I ſay to Rome, even vnto that Rome, which they call <hi>impure;</hi> for, if they haue writen truly, no man can deny to enter commons with them, even in thoſe things which theſe Opponents call impure; becauſe from them we may argue thus, the Romiſh Church can yeild ſalvation to her members, therfore it is the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt way to ioyn to her, ſeeing all ſides agree in the Antecedent, but, vnſafe it is, to ioyn with other Churches; for 'tis doubtfull
<pb facs="tcp:18310:10"/>and in queſtion, whether ſalvation can there be had or no; and thus ſome of that Church haue reaſoned againſt vs; if any ſay, with vs is perfection, and puritie of doctrine; with them, is he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, and defection, he ſaith <hi>Nothing ſufficient to keepe vs from Rome;</hi> becauſe, if there were any power herein for that end, it is, becauſe, their hereſie, and defection, (in the event) is able to hinder ſalvation: but the Romiſh hereſie, and defection, (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to theſe Opponents) is not able (in the event) to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſalvation; becauſe, with them <hi>The foundation is held, which hath the property of that wine, which will not mingle with poyſon, though a great quantity thereof be put vnto it, yea, ſuch an Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote it is and a thing ſo ſoveraigne, that, it will deſtroy much poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and at laſt quite overcome it.</hi> If all this be true, who would not be a Papiſt; ſeeing with them we finde enough to perſuade vs; for who would not yeeld to tread the way to heaven? and nothing to diſſwade vs: for no wiſe man will be afraid of the thing that cannot hurt him: and this is the caſe betweene the Romiſh Church and vs; if theſe Opponents may be believed: if they ſay, They did not perceiue the iſſue of their doctrine, then muſt we blame them as heedleſſe, and inconſiderate; what, will they be our <hi>Iuſtructers? Shall their I reatiſes ſerue to giue vs Instruction? Shall</hi> Cato <hi>be compelled to come in, and ſee, and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure:</hi> and yet ſuch fowle, and groſſe faults bee committed. Moreover, if ſalvation may be had in the Romiſh Church, and their hereſies cannot hinder it, then doubtleſſe, there is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Intely nothing ſufficient to bar vs their communion: ſeeing they doe as ſtrongly avouch their doctrine to be pure, as theſe Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponents doe condemne it as impure: In this caſe, what ſhall moſt men living doe, if they be ſeduced to Popery? If a Prieſt ſhould ſay, with vs thou maiſt goe to heaven, (as your owne ſide confeſſe) with vs is nothing to preſſe thee downe to hell: for, though we were as bad as you make vs, yet by the confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of yours, we haue an Antidote that in the event will preſerue thee from the evill, and reſerue thee for the good. Laſtly, it can not appeare that we are blamed iuſtly: for, how much you ſay againſt vs, ſo much (if not more) we can ſay for vs; we haue the Records of all ages for vs, Councels, Fathers, hiſtory, are ſtrongly on our ſide; we haue alledged them, and you cannot
<pb facs="tcp:18310:11"/>gainſay vs: ſo as, now, either ſatisfie this laſt, or yeeld to ioyne wich vs: for, your ſelues doe teach the two firſt, and you may not deny them; now, in this caſe, what can a reaſonable man doe? He ſees nothing but doubtfull, and difficult queſtions to keepe him from Popery, and himſelfe not able to determine thoſe doubts; I ſay, who would not reſolue thus? I will ioyne with them, not with you; ſeeing I haue nothing to debarr me, but ſome doubtfull queſtions that may be true, and may not be true; yet howſoever they cannot hurt me.</p>
            <p>If theſe Opponents would haue vs belieue,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> (as they greatlyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire) that, they are enemies to <hi>Rome,</hi> and friends to vs, they muſt haue eſteemed the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to want the nature of that Church whereof Chriſt is the head: for, that makes all ſure, that barrs the doore, and ſhutteth vp all entrance vnto her, no man will be ſo mad to joyn with that ſociety, where he knowes the eſſence or nature of Chriſts Church is wanting; ſeeing in ſuch a ſociety, ſalvation cannot be had. It is a rule caſe in nature, <hi>No man will come to his loſſe; and 'tis as true in the ſtate of grace, no man will venture where he ſhall loſe heaven.</hi> But, becauſe we finde not this, they muſt giue vs leaue to oppoſe them as enemies, not receiue them as friends, leſt their friendſhip turnes to bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe at the laſt end.</p>
            <p>They would perſuade vs,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> that, <hi>Their opinion of the Romiſh Church is burtfull vnto her, becauſe, therein they quit her with mercy, in ſtead of her cruelty: ſhe condemneth vs wholly, we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne her but in part.</hi> But, this commends their cauſe but little: for according to our common Proverbe, <hi>Fooliſh pitty ſpoiles a whole City:</hi> and this is their caſe: <hi>Fooliſh is their pity, becauſe Gods word, and true reaſon does abhorre it, (at least) does not avow it. Spoile</hi> it doth, yea the <hi>whole City</hi> of God, (at leaſt ſo farre as it is able) becauſe it opens, I will not ſay a wicket, but the wideſt doore to Popery; and ſtandeth alſo in that doore, and in the high wayes like the ſtrumpet, to call in, adulterous lovers; as I haue already ſhewed: but let this pitty condemne them of cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, (as for this time I am content it ſhall) yet the Romiſh Church hath no hurt by it: for, it condemnes them of a fault in the practiſe of good manners, wherein the nature of the Church conſiſteth not, it meddles not with their faith, wherein
<pb facs="tcp:18310:11"/>the Church conſiſteth. The truth is, their opinion of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church is not loue, nor pitty: for, if it be their due, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they haue indeed that eſſence, and nature wherewith Chriſts Church is formed, then it is Iuſtice, (which conſiſteth in giving every man his due:) If it be not their due, becauſe they want that eſſence or nature wherewith Chriſts Church is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, then it is a lye, which alwayes is committed, when a man pronounceth of a thing otherwiſe then it is in it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>They plead, <hi>That, we miſtake them indeed,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> and in the thing they agree with vs; becauſe, there is one truth naturall, and another mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall; they holde the queſtion in the firſt ſenſe, and we in the ſecond: but, vpon adviſement, and a true vnderſtanding of thins, we ſay as they doe, and they as we; both concurring in this, that, the Romiſh Church hath the eſſence or being of Chriſts Church, but defiled with hereſy, and idolatry.</hi> The caſe ſtands not thus, we vnderſtand them to ſay, <hi>The Romiſh Church hath that eſſence, and nature wherewith the Church of Chriſt is conſtituted and formed.</hi> And vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and all her right bred children ſay the contradictory, as ſhall evidently appeare in the diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it ſelfe, when we propound, explicate, and agree vpon, the ſtate of the queſtion: wherefore, let not our Opponents ſhrowd themſelues vnder our ignorant miſtaking of their meaning in the preſent queſtion; for we ſhall depriue them thereof, and leaue them naked vnto the wide world, when we come to the place aforeſaid, where the Reader ſhall finde, that we accept the queſtion, even in their owne termes, and as themſelues doe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicate, and vnfold it: wherein we doe no new thing; for our Church had vſed the like explication before them, as the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſhall perceiue in the place forenamed. Theſe things being true, (as they are moſt true) it was a poore ſhift, to caſt vpon vs, the ſhamefull reproach of miſtaking their meaning, as if, we were ignorant, and could not, or malicious, and would not or over zealous and did not, vnderſtand their writing: we vſe to ſay, <hi>Better a bad ſhift, then none at all:</hi> all we may anſwere it with the like; <hi>A ſhameleſſe ſhift, is worſe then none at all:</hi> and this is the preſent caſe: when all meanes faile, we muſt be ignorant, malicious, or over zealous miſtakers of their meaning, rather then they will be ſeene to meane falſely; their doings ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb facs="tcp:18310:12"/>friends aſunder, reconcileth not, nor bring them together.</p>
            <p>Hitherto we haue taken as granted,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> that, theſe Opponents doe maintaine a poſition contradictory to our Church. It may be, they will deny it, and plead thus for themſelues.</p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>England</hi> ſaith thus.</p>
            <q>The Romiſh Church hath not the nature of the true Church.</q>
            <p>We ſay thus.</p>
            <q>The Romiſh Church hath not the nature of a true Church.</q>
            <p>She ſaith, <hi>The Church:</hi> we ſay, <hi>A Church.</hi> I haue not found this exception made as yet by any, yet it is very needfull, that I propound it, and giue anſwere herevnto; Some man (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) will attempt his eſcape by it; for, vntruthes of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, muſt creepe into the pooreſt corner, rather then remaine without ſhelter. If there be no differrence betweene <hi>The na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a true Church,</hi> and <hi>the nature of the true Church,</hi> then both theſe ſentences are the ſame, and accordingly, they deny what our Church doth affirme; but they are the ſame, for Chriſts Church (howſoever it be taken, and with what word ſoever, it be donoted, and ſet out) is form'd and conſtituted, by one and the ſame formall eſſence, and being, otherwiſe, there ſhould be two Churches of Chriſt ſpecifically form'd, and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferenced: which yet, God never revealed, we never haue read, and no man therefore may avouch. If the word <hi>[A]</hi> and the word <hi>[The]</hi> import one ſpecificall thing, then the Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in queſtion are contradictorie: becauſe, the ſame predicate is affirmed of the ſame ſubiect in the one, and ſo denied in the other: but, both theſe words import the ſame thing; for, a perticular Church is called <hi>[A Church]</hi> in the common vſe of men; and ſo it is called <hi>[The Church]</hi> by the Apoſtle; <hi>The Church that is in thy houſe</hi> Moreover, though the words <hi>[A Church]</hi> did make a difference from the words <hi>[The Church]</hi> yet the predicate part of both theſe propoſitions are ſtill the ſame, for, that difference can be no more, <hi>then generall or vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall, and perticuler.</hi> which in this place makes no difference in the predicates, which conſiſteth (cheiſly) in the <hi>terme na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or eſſence:</hi> and that is the ſame in the Church, taken as a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick,
<pb facs="tcp:18310:12"/>or vniuerſall comprehenſion of all the members, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Church conſiſteth, or conceiued in perticuler, as it is bounded and limited within one Nation. This I ſay, the Church <hi>Catholick,</hi> and the Church <hi>Nationall,</hi> or <hi>O Econumicall,</hi> is formed and conſtituted by one and the ſame formall eſſence, and being, they only differ materially, whoſe propertie it is, to individuate the forme materiated. And ſence it ſelfe doth teach it vs, every ſinguler man, and every diſtinct Nation and all men without exception, haue one and the ſame ſpecificall, and formall being, Intelligibillitie, and Ellectuallitie, is the ſame in one man, &amp; in all men, herin only they differ; the one is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of many individuall bodies, the other a comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a few individuall bodies, ſo is it with Chriſts Church, the ſame thing that makes that whole ſocietie to be Chriſts Church ſpecifically, and formally, the very ſame thing makes a Nation, or a fewer number, to be Chriſts Church ſpecifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, and formally: by reaſon whereof, when we deny, <hi>The Romiſh Church to haue the nature of the Church,</hi> we deny it to haue <hi>the nature of A Church.</hi> And contrariwiſe, when we ſay, <hi>The Romiſh Church hath the nature of a true Church,</hi> we giue her <hi>the nature of the true Church,</hi> and thus (I hope) I haue preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all men that would doubt whether theſe Opponents doe contradict our Church or not, and haue made it manifeſt, that they doe contradict her indeed, and accordingly we haue here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, and may hereafter, rightly, and iuſtly, preſume it as true, and take it as certeine, and thus am I well neere at an end in my anſwere to all their paſſages in common: Two onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines, I will ſpeak breifely vnto them, and then finiſh this matter.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the reſt of their hard meaſure offered vnto vs,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> I find one heape which may not be concealed: in 15. ſhort lines, thus are we ſtiled.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Your mindes are prepoſſeſſed with preiudiced. They content themſelues only to take vp opinions vpon truſt, and will hold them, becauſe they know where they had them.</p>
               <p>Whole volumes are nothing vnto them,</p>
               <p>Anuiles they are, &amp; in vaine ſhould I ſpend my ſelfe in beating vpon them.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18310:13"/>
               <p>Chriſtians they are not ingenuous.</p>
               <p>They haue no care open for Iuſtice, and truth.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Doubtleſſe this Opponent meant to infer ſomething from this rabble: for, a man of wiſdome, and learning will not ſpeak words that ſerue to no purpoſe. I conceiue he would conclude thus.</p>
            <q>Therefore our adverſaries cauſe is naught.</q>
            <p>This was once Biſhop <hi>Iewels</hi> caſe, when he had to doe with <hi>rayling Harding;</hi> to whom he anſwered thus: <hi>I pray thee good Reader, thinke not our cauſe the worſe, though theſe mens tongues are ſo ready to ſpeake ill, content thy ſelfe a while, and thou ſhalt ſee all this ſmoake blowne away, even with one blaſt.</hi> In whoſe words I anſwer too. Theſe ignominious termes are nothing to inferr ſuch a concluſion: for evill men may ſpeake the truth, and defend a good cauſe: Wherefore the naughtineſſe of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon inferreth not badneſſe vpon a cauſe, or queſtion. The Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent is alſo falſe, we deny our ſelues to be guilty as he doth charge vs, he brings no proofe for his indictment, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt be pronounced <hi>Rectius in Curia:</hi> and ſo every ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man (who hath his eyes in his head) will ſay of vs: for, if accuſation can make guilty, who ſhall be innocent. Thus, theſe pleaders Argument is come to nothing, like ſmoake carryed vp with the ayre.</p>
            <p>But let vs reaſon the caſe with him a little;
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> Is this Authour bitter by cuſtome? Is his nature addicted to ſharpneſſe? My ſelfe am not able to reſolue the doubt: if he be, we willingly pardon the offence, we muſt <hi>beare one anothers burthen,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Apoſtles rule. Nay, we will pray in the words of the firſt Chriſtian Martyr, and ſay, <hi>O Lord forgiue him, for he knowes not what he does:</hi> his paſſion was at this time his maſter: but if this ill language be acted, if it be taken vp to ſerue a turn, the caſe is worſe for him, his account (before Gods Tribunall) is the greater and heavier; but for vs the better, his impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſhall commend our patience, his bitterneſſe our meekneſſe; his crying in the ſtreets, our ſilence; beſt it is to be like him, that as a lambe dumbe before the ſhearer, ſo was he, and open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not his mouth. And thus much is enough for this paſſage.</p>
            <p>The laſt thing which comes in our way, is our Opponents
<pb facs="tcp:18310:13"/>inſulting and vaunting termes, conteined in the title of of his booke, and the end of his Engliſh Epiſtle; which I haue repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in this Preface, num. 3. and theſe they are.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>He is an Inſtructer.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>His Treatiſe ſerues to giue inſtruction.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>With him is the Spirit.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The inſpiration of the Almighty giues him vnderſtanding, and him onely, for ſometimes great men want w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me, and the aged vnderſtanding, and iudgement; therefore you muſt heare him.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For his writings, they are ſuch, as he may let</hi> Cato <hi>come in, and ſee, and cenſure.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>We haue now the head, but we want the tayle: he preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs with an Antecdent, but his pocket holds the concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a conſequent. Is he wiſe in that? Surely, a wiſe Logician I grant, for no man would doe thus, but he that excells in that art. But what ſay I? Doe I commend him for Logick? I doe: but 'tis my fault, and I craue his pardon: when he diſputes I muſt extoll him, for his Rethorick: for, with him, that art is the queene of arts to ſerue a Diſputers terme; and no doubt ſhe was his queene and he followed her lawes when he would thus extoll himſelfe. Doubtleſſe, hereby he meant to abaſe vs, and our cauſe, elſe it had beene vaine, thus to elevate himſelfe: and we will confeſſe (for our owne parts) that we muſt come vnder his ſee, and hide our ſelues vnder him from the weather ſhore; if all be true that he avoucheth: but I doubt of that, and ſo muſt, till I heare <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> his ſentence; for, he commits the cauſe to him, and ſo will we too: becauſe <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ato</hi> (amongſt all Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers) is held, the wiſeſt, and graveſt Stateſman and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker: therefore we will preſent his particular braggs, and attend the ſentence of <hi>Cato.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He appeales to <hi>Cato,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> nay he invites yea provokes <hi>Cato</hi> to the ſearch and cenſure of his writings. Even he, this Authour, a youth, as him elfe profeſſeth, and all the world knowes, he is a yoncker and but a yoncker in age, and ſtadies: what will <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> ſay to this? The excellenteſt of many, muſt riſe from his graue, to cenſure the meaneſt of thouſands. Let him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18310:14"/>
            <p>An inſtructer he is, but will you know what degree he beares in that office; his title will tell you, even nothing infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to God himſelfe: for he borrowed his whole title from <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32: 1. onely God calls his worke a Pſalme, this Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent names his, a treatiſe, but one thing he comes ſhort in, that word MASCHIL in the Hebrew is written two ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall waies; in the one it fignifies to vnderſtand, or things fit to be vnderſtood, If it be written the ſecond way, it ſignifies lightneſſe, folly, or to be mad, as the learned in that tongue, haue obſerved. Thus much I baue beene informed by men of credit in that language, for my ſelfe am wholly ignorant that way: things ſtanding thus, I ſay if he had written that word with the Hebrew Character, we ſhould haue vnderſtood his meaning, we might haue knowne the full value of his ſtile, and title of honour, but becauſe he hath not, we can onely gueſſe at it: wherefore thus we ſay, if we take it to ſignifie things fit to giue vnderſtanding, then in this office he giues God the mate, what will <hi>Cato</hi> ſay to this, that a Youth (not 30. yeares of age) becomes an inſtructer equall to God himſelfe. No mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell though he dares <hi>Cato</hi> to his face, ſeeing he dare ſet his foote to Gods, and inſtruct in things divine equall to him: if he writes the word the ſecond way, then folly is his name, and madneſſe is with him.</p>
            <p>But,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> who is it that he offers to inſtruct? Not ſchollers in a Grammar ſchoole: no no: theſe are to meane for him to worke vpon; It is his Mother whome he muſt deale withall, his Mother (I ſay) that bred him, and nouriſheth him, muſt be ſubiect now to his rod, and ferula; O happy Mother may ſhe well ſay, that hath ſuch a Child: ſo ripe, that in ſo few yeares can inſtruct his Mother; and thrice happy Sonne, that is growne vp with ſuch ſpeed, that ſo ſoone as he can but crawle, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently can ſuſtaine and ſuccour his Mother: I know this will be <hi>Catoes</hi> ſentence, therefore <hi>Cato,</hi> ſpeake and ſpare not, wee know thou wilt ſay as we doe, therefore we will heare and feare not.</p>
            <p>He telleth vs:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> 
               <hi>Gods Spirit dwels with him and by the inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof, he hath vnderſtanding. Therefore he muſt speake, you
<pb facs="tcp:18310:14"/>you muſt not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eare them;</hi> If he proue the Antecedent, I grant the conſequent, but that he cannot; nay 'tis impoſſible. <hi>Gods ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is fish</hi> of temperance, humility, meekneſſe, kindeneſſe loue, ſo as, he that is taught by that Maiſter, hath learned theſe leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; His ſchollers are not <hi>proud, vaine boſters of themſelues, their minds are not lifted v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n them: but they eſteeme others bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then themſelue:</hi> If we lay our preſent Opponent to this rule, in what caſe ſhall we find him: agrees he with it? Does he notſwarue from it? Let this title and concluſion of his Epiſtle giue Iudgement, I ſay no more: though I know <hi>Cato</hi> would ſay no leſſe; yea we are ſure, he would exceed us much, and thus am I come to an end of my anſwere to ſuch things as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the diſputation in common, and therefore I will proceed in the next place, to a formall diſpute of the queſtion it ſelfe.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:18310:15"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18310:15"/>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 1. <hi>Of the queſtion and parties to the diſputation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the following diſcourſe we inquire after theſe two queſtions.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Whether the preſent <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, be the true Church or not.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Whether the profeſſors of the preſent <hi>Romiſh</hi> faith, can be ſaved or not.</p>
               <p>Theſe two doe mutually imply each other. So as we may truely ſay, if ſhe be a Church, then is there ſaluation in her, if ſalvation, then a Church, and contrarywiſe, wherefore the proofe of the firſt confirmes the latter.</p>
               <p>The parties to the preſent diſputation are,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> our Church and all her true and lawfull children, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the one part: And two of her vnnatutall chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren make the other part. Which of them hath the truth, I hope (by Gods grace) openly to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, before we end this Treatiſe.</p>
               <p>Our Church holds the negatiue in the firſt que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, and hath ſet her ſentences downe in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Homilie</hi> for <hi>whitſontide</hi> in theſe words</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>The ſtate of the preſent Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>is ſo far wide from the nature of the true Church, that nothing can be more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>The Biſhops of</hi> Rome <hi>and their adherents, are not the true Church of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:18310:16"/>3 <hi>The true Church is not at</hi> Rome.</p>
               <p>The firſt and ſecond of the alledged ſentences, are expreſſely found barely ſet downe as I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged them, and they are ſufficient to let vs know the faith of our Church in the matter in hand.</p>
               <p>The third, is neceſſarily implyed by our Church at theſe words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If it be poſs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ble for Gods ſpirit to be there where the true Church is not then is it at</hi> Rome.</p>
               <p>In this latter ſentence our Church preſumes, that the true Church is not at <hi>Rome,</hi> otherwiſe the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence would be fond and ridiculous, and indeed the Diſputation in that place being framed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Art ſtandeth thus.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Where the holy Ghoſt is, there is the true Church.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>But at</hi> Rome, <hi>there is not the true Church.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Therefore the holy Ghoſt is not at</hi> Rome,</item>
               </list>
               <p>The Propoſition is purſued after the words laſt alledged, the Aſſumption is confirmed by argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments going before.</p>
               <p>Thus our Church by repeating the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion often, ſheweth vs how ſerious ſhe is in the matter, and by often varying her manner of ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, we cleerely vnderſtand her meaning.</p>
               <p>The foreſaid two opponents doe hold the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatiue againſt our Church,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> namely:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Church of</hi> Rome <hi>as ſhe is at this preſent, is a true Church.</hi> As page 30 in the one, and page 18. in the other.</p>
               <p>Before we enter vpon the diſcuſſion hereof,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> we muſt firſt vnderſtand the termes wherein this queſtion is delivered.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:18310:16"/>
               <p>By <hi>Romiſh Church,</hi> we meane the <hi>Biſhops of Rome and their adherents,</hi> (that is to ſay) <hi>all ſuch both Clergie and Laytie, which liue in the Romiſh Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and communicate in her faith, and make vp one ſociety or body.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>By true Church, <hi>we vnderſtand</hi> a Society or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, which hath theſe eſſentiall qualities that concurre vnto the being and forme of a Church,</q>
               <p>And herein all ſides agree as the Reader may finde in the <hi>Homilie</hi> alledged, and in both our op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponents in page 13 of the one, and page 15, 17. and 100. of the other. We muſt alſo further knowe, that the <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>miſh</hi> faith conſiſteth, either in the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall conſent of their learned, or in the Decrees of their Councels, or in both.</p>
               <p>The firſt is their Catholick, the ſecond is their divine faith. So as he that profeſſeth their religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and communicates in their faith, beleeues as they doe in the manner aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>Hitherto I haue alledged the <hi>Homilie,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> as the doctrine of our Church, and I preſume none will reproue me for it, becauſe all that booke, is ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confirmed as ſuch by our State, It is to be read in all our Churches by publike appointment, and is ſubſcribed vnto by all our Miniſters, as contein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Doctrine, godly, wholeſome, and neceſſary,</hi> I ſay, it is ſo ſubſcribed vnto, becauſe the 36 <hi>Canon</hi> requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, <hi>that no perſon ſhalbe received into the Miniſtry; nor ſuffered to exerciſe any part of the Miniſteriall function in any place within this Realme, except he ſhall firſt ſubſcribe (amongſt other things) vnto the</hi> 39 <hi>Articles
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18310:17"/>of Religion, agreed vpon by the whole Clergy Anno</hi> 1562. Now the 36 <hi>Canon</hi> in commanding ſubſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the ſaid 39 Articles, doth alſo conſequently command ſubſcription to the bookes of <hi>Homilies,</hi> becauſe <hi>the</hi> 35 <hi>Article doth no more but ratifie &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the former and ſecond booke of Homilies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now if the preſent <hi>Homilie</hi> be the doctrine of our Church, then the ſentences alledged out of the ſame can be no leſſe, for they are ſuch a maine and principall part thereof, that the <hi>Homilie</hi> cannot ſubſiſt without them. And thus I hope every Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hath direction enough, touching the ſtate of the queſtion and the parties to the Diſputation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 2. <hi>Of our firſt Argument for the maine queſtion, and of their generall anſwer thereunto.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OVr Church in the <hi>Homilie</hi> already recited,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> hath an argument expreſly thus.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>The true Church is built vpon the foundation of the Apoſtles, and Prophets, Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the head corner stone.</item>
                  <item>But the preſent Romiſh Church, is not built vpon the foundation of the Apoſtles and Prophets, for they reteyne not the ſound and pure doctrine of Chriſt Ieſu, neither do they order the Sacraments in ſuch ſort, as he did firſt inſtitute and ordeyne them, that now they may ſeeme to be converted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a new guiſe.</item>
                  <item>Therefore the preſent <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, is not the true Church.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:18310:17"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> Homilie <hi>takes the propoſition to be a diſcription of the Church, ſo rgreeable to the Scriptures, and Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers, that none may iuſtly find fault therewith. So likewiſe it takes the Aſſumption, as a confeſſed truth by all ſuch as haue any light of Gods word, and inſight into their liues, and examples. Whereupon it is confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of the concluſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though this Argument wanteth not ſtrength, to inferre the concluſion,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ſo as it needeth not our further labour, yet before I paſſe from it, I will vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold the termes.</p>
               <p>By <hi>Chriſt and his ſeruants,</hi> not their perſons, but their Preaching and Revelation is vnderſtood.</p>
               <p>The ſacred Revelation, is called the <hi>Churches foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation,</hi> becauſe by the profeſſion therof, the Church is made to be that which it is, and is differenced from all other Societies in the world, and good reaſon, becauſe by the profeſſion of the divine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, the Church is ordered vnto heaven, which befalleth no Societie elſe whatſoever, the <hi>Homilie</hi> ſpeaks of the <hi>foundation of the Church,</hi> as one intire &amp; individuall whole, that is, of one complete being vndivided into parts or kinds, and it attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes the ſame in the Propoſition to the true Church, as adequate thereunto, and convertible therewith, and it denyes it in the Aſſumption, vnto the preſent Romiſh Church vniuerſally, or totally. So as the Church of Rome, and the Sacred Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation in the intent of the <hi>Homilie,</hi> are divided as things really, and eſſentially, diſtinct and different, as if our Church had ſaid, the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church ſitteth beſides the foundation of the Divine Revelation.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:18310:18"/>
               <p>And thus our Church muſt be vnderſtood, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this ſence agrees with the Scriptures, with the 39 Article, and with true reaſon, all other ſences are violent and inforced as we ſhall ſee in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of this Argument.</p>
               <p>According to this interpretation,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may be framed in theſe termes.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>The true Church profeſſeth the Preaching, or Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of Chriſt, and his Apoſtles.</item>
                  <item>The preſent <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church profeſſeth not the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching or Revelation of Chriſt and his Apoſtles,</item>
                  <item>Therefore the preſent <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, is not the true Church.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Our opponent <hi>B.</hi> againſt this Argument pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth thus,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> he denyes not but after a ſort confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, that this Argument is our Churches, pa. 83. and ſo fareth it with his partner our opponent <hi>C.</hi> pag 21. our opponent <hi>B,</hi> in his Engliſh Epiſtle, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes the concluſion of this Argument to bee our Churches, but the opponent <hi>C</hi> ſaith nothing.</p>
               <p>I anſwer,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> how can the opponent <hi>B.</hi> ſay, our Church holds not the concluſion, who confeſſed even now, that our Church made the Argument, vnleſſe he will ſay, that the concluſion of an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is no part thereof. If that be his iudgement, he muſt teach <hi>Aristotle,</hi> for he thinketh otherwiſe. <hi>Prior. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Top: lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. For this time the concluſion ſhall goe for none of hers, that we may ſee what they will ſay to it.</p>
               <p>Opponent <hi>B.</hi> in his Latine Epiſtle ſayes,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He that thinks the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>to be no Church, thinks nothing.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:18310:18"/>
               <p>His partner <hi>C.</hi> in his Epiſtle Dedicatory, profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, <hi>that he trembles at the very hearing of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, [the preſent Romiſh Church is no Church.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſure, theſe parties are ill matched, becauſe they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>roſſe one the other. The one thinks the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent concluſion to be nothing, the other eſteemes it a monſter, and that is more then ſome thing, but let vs for this time thinke ſo too, becauſe if that be ſo, then the premiſes which inferre that conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion are monſtrous likewiſe, if the premiſes bee monſtrous, then will theſe opponents make them to appeare to be ſo. And thus much for their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to this Argument in generall.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 3. <hi>Of the ſame Argument and their anſwer thereunto.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Reader muſt remember our Argument,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> in the true and plaineſt termes ſtandeth thus.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>The true Church is founded vpon (that is) profeſſeth, the ſacred truth revealed by Chriſt and his Apoſtles.</item>
                  <item>But the preſent Romiſh Church is not ſo founded,</item>
                  <item>Therefore the preſent <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, is not the true Church.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Our opponent <hi>C.</hi> anſwereth hereunto, pag 21,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 22. with theſe very words.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Theſe words muſt receiue this conſtruction.</p>
                  <p>Firſt they muſt be vnderſtood of the accidentall truth of the Church, in regard of ſoundnes, and not of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18310:19"/>eſſentiall truth, in regard of Gods Covenant.</p>
                  <p>Secondly they muſt be vnderſtood even of ſoundnes, comparatiuely and not ſimply, that is in regard of the Primitiue Church, and not otherwiſe.</p>
               </q>
               <p>Thus farre he and not one word further touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this matter.</p>
               <p>I reply,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> In this anſwer we muſt looke for the meaning of his words, and the application of the matter to our Argument. His meaning is further to ſeeke then <hi>Sampſons</hi> Riddle, or more ſenſeleſſe then becomes a reaſonable man.</p>
               <p>He ſeemes thus to diſtinguiſh.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The truth of the Church is
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Accidentall in regard of ſoundneſſe.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Eſſentiall in regard of Gods Couenant.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. Soundnes is taken
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Comparatiuely in regard of the Primitiue Church.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Simply.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>For thus lyes his words directly: but who ſhall vnderſtand him? The Rules of Logicke cannot help vs, for according to them, theſe diſtributions are no wayes to be allowed.</p>
               <p>According to Art, every diſtribution contein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a whole, and part. So <hi>Ariſtotle Top. lib:</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Rurſus vtrum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> &amp;c.</hi> cap. 2. <hi>Idem contingens:</hi> ſo <hi>Ramus lib.</hi> 1. cap. 25. But here is no whole and part, for <hi>a whole is no more but a gathering together of the parts,</hi> ſo <hi>as they all doe make one certaine thing.</hi> Thus <hi>Ariſt. Phyſico: lib.</hi> 1. <hi>tex.</hi> 17. <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>tex.</hi> 43. <hi>meta. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 25. <hi>tex.</hi> 31. Thus <hi>Th.</hi> 1. <hi>q.</hi> 76. <hi>art.</hi> 8. <hi>in cor.</hi> &amp; ſo <hi>Ramus lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 25. But in theſe diſtributions, there is no whole and parts.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:18310:19"/>
               <p>Moreover,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> in the firſt diſtinction <hi>truth</hi> is the thing divided, and that is ſet out by the terme <hi>Church,</hi> (that is) the adiunct or accident is ſet out by a firſt ſubſtance or individuall ſubiect. If that be good, then <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> muſt come to him to learne Logick: for (according to him) <hi>all other things are attributed to a ſingular being, and that attributed to none. Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor. cap.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5. <hi>Prior. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 27. <hi>poſt lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 22.</p>
               <p>Againe,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> in that diſtribution eſſentiall and acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentall are made parts of truth; but that is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, for truth is no more but <hi>the adequation of the thing, and the apprehenſion of our vnderſtanding,</hi> in the Iudgement of <hi>Ariſtotle de interpre cap.</hi> 9. <hi>&amp; meta lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>text.</hi> 27. <hi>&amp; Thomas</hi> 1. <hi>p. q.</hi> 21. <hi>art.</hi> 2. <hi>in cor.</hi> 1. <hi>Diſt.</hi> 46. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>art.</hi> 2. <hi>ad</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">m</hi>. But <hi>accidentall</hi> and <hi>eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall truth makes no ſuch adequation:</hi> for thoſe termes import no more but a neceſſary and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingent predication which belongs to the manner of predicating.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Laſtly, he attributes</hi> ſoundneſſe to accidentall truth, <hi>and</hi> Gods covenant to eſſentiall truth; <hi>but that is impoſſible.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>The ſecond diſtribution is as fond,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> if not worſe then the firſt, but I will not miſpend mine owne and the Readers time about it. It was meet for mee to let this opponent ſee his weakneſſe in Logick, becauſe he vaunteth ſo much of his skill that waies in his Epiſtle, and throughout his whole booke.</p>
               <p>We ſhould now come to the application of this anſwer to ſome part of our argument,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> that we might know what he denies, and what he grants,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18310:20"/>and why: but I am altogether to ſeeke for that, becauſe he brings nothing that leades vs thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: Wherefore I come to himſelfe and ſay in his owne words, pag. 3. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Apply Iohn Barber, and thou ſhalt haue a new paire of S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>zors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When he hath done ſo he ſhall haue further an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, and in the meane time I will ſet downe and examine what his partner <hi>B.</hi> ſaith to our argument now in hand; therein I will take onely the ſumme of his anſwer and no more, to ſaue mine owne labour and the Readers, following the example of the ſchooles, who alwayes run that courſe.</p>
               <p>He beginneth his anſwer at p. 84. at theſe words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We profeſſe that we eſteem,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> &amp;c.</hi> And continues the ſame vnto pag. 88. As his partners anſwer was, ſo is his, intricate, perplexed, vnapplyed, but with this difference he was briefer, as liking Logick and not Rethorick, this larger, as loving Rethorick and not Logick, nothing could be made of his. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing as I conceiue may be made of this, wherefore I will ſet downe that ſomething with the beſt war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of his owne diſcourſe. Thus then he ſeemes to anſwere.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>The doctrine of Chriſt and his Apoſtles purely taught without mixture of error is the genuine marke of the true Church: So as, where that is, there followes the appellation of a true Church, and from thence we may argue thus.</p>
                  <p>Whereſoever Gods word is purely preached, and the Sacraments duly adminiſtred, there is a true Church.</p>
                  <p>And ſo farre the Propoſition is true and agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18310:20"/>to the intent of our Church, and the Aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ſo alſo that ſevereth the doctrine of Chriſt from the preſent Romiſh Church, but then the concluſion importeth no more but that ſhe is not an orthodox Church which is not in queſtion.</p>
                  <p>The doctrine of Chriſt and his Apoſtles taught purely without mixture of errour is not ſo eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall to the true Church that ſo ſoone as vnſound doctrine is mingled with the truth of Gods word and the Sacraments vnduely adminiſtred that which was a Church ſhould ceaſe to be one.</p>
                  <p>In this ſenſe the Propoſition is falſe, for ſuch doctrine belongs vnto the perfection and glory of the Church, and ſhe may be without them as the children of Iſrael were many dayes without a Sacrifice and an Ephod. Hoſea. <hi>3.4.</hi> yet ſtill they were Gods Church.</p>
                  <p>It may fall out that they may be corrupted as in the times of blindneſſe and ſuperſtition, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termitted as in perſecution.</p>
                  <p>In this ſenſe the Propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is not according to the intent of our Church which meant not ſo ſtrictly to tye Gods Church to theſe ſignes as if all were excluded from the Church which doe not rightly participate of the word and Sacraments in the Iudgement of <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Rogers</hi> in his Commentary vpon <hi>19.</hi> art. propo. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly, in this ſenſe the Aſſumption is falſe that makes a reall &amp; totall diviſion between the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Romiſh Church &amp; all revealed truth, we ſay ſhe hath not aboliſhed all truth, but retaineth ſome in their diſputations, and as we thinke more in their Sermons.</p>
               </q>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:18310:21"/>
               <p>Thus I hope I haue exactly expreſſed his intent, if I haue miſſed in any thing the fault is his, not mine; he may thanke me for my paines, becauſe <hi>I haue done for him what he could not, (at least) what he hath not done for himſelfe:</hi> that I may vſe his partners words, pag. 5.</p>
               <p>Now we will take it into ſeverall peeces, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine them in ſeverall chapters following.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 4. Prooving this ſentence, <hi>The preſent Romiſh faith is erronius.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe examination of his laſt anſwer to our Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> (wherin he does attribute ſome pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Chriſts doctrine vnto the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>) is ſufficient to determine the worth of our argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment now in hand, and the whole queſtion it ſelfe: for if the Romiſh Church be all errour and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian, (that is) if her faith be erronious, then without doubt ſhe is none of Gods Church. The Church of England in her Aſſumption (now in queſtion) meant to ſay ſo, as I haue already ſaid, <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>n.</hi> 1. and will now prooue by Gods aſſiſtance.</p>
               <p>If the Romiſh Church retaine ſome of Chriſts doctrine pure without mixture of errour,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> then, 1. Chriſts doctrine cannot be denied her in termes without limitation. 2. She is not changed into a new guiſe, nor hath forſaken the commandements of God to ſet vp her owne conſtitutions. 3. She is
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18310:21"/>not without the holy Ghoſt. But (according to our Church) 1. <hi>Chriſts doctrine is denied her in terms</hi> without limitation: for thus lye the words of her Aſſumption: <hi>The preſent Romiſh Church is not built vpon the foundation of the Apoſtles and Prophets, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the ſound and pure doctrine of Chriſt Ieſu, neither doe they order the Sacraments in ſuch ſort as he did firſt inſtitute and ordaine them.</hi> 2. <hi>She is chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into a new guiſe by chopping and changing, by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and plucking away. They haue forſaken the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of God to ſet vp their owne conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> 3. <hi>They are without the Spirit of God.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (according to our Church in her Aſſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) the preſent Romiſh Church does not retaine ſome part of Chriſts doctrine pure without mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of errour, but ſhe is all errour, and her faith erronious.</p>
               <p>Many learned amongſt vs haue ſo vnderſtood our Church, and I will name ſome in ſtead of all.</p>
               <p>Biſhop <hi>Iewell</hi> in the defence of his Apology, <hi>pag.</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. <hi>diviſ.</hi> 1. chargeth her in abſolute termes, that <hi>ſhe had departed from Gods ward:</hi> and more plainly, <hi>pag.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 13. <hi>diviſ.</hi> He ſaith the ſame thing in theſe words. <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe men haue br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ken in pecces all the popes and conduits, they haue ſtopped all the ſprings and choaked vp the fountaine of living water with dirt and myre.</hi> He repeates the ſame thing in other termes, <hi>cap.</hi> 15. <hi>diviſ.</hi> 2. thus. <hi>In the Romiſh Church we cannot home the word of God ſinetrely taught, nor the Sacraments rightly adminiſtred, nor the name of God duely called vpon, and wherein was nothing able to ſtay any wiſe man, or one that hath conſideration of his own</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:18310:22"/>ſafety, I will conclude with his words in the ſame <hi>Apologie part</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 22. <hi>diviſ.</hi> 2. where he ſaith, that <hi>the preſent Church of Rome hath vtterly forſaken the Catholike faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doct. Reynolds</hi> in his 5. <hi>Concluſions</hi> &amp; <hi>Preface,</hi> at the 6. doth charge the preſent Romiſh Church to be <hi>diſtempered not with a ſickneſſe that hindreth the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of life, but with ſuch a one, as for it ſelfe makes her paſt hope of recouery; and namely ſhe ſerues not God with a holy worſhip, nor beleeved God with a holy faith as he hath commanded, but ſtained the faith of Chriſt with reproaches, creatures with the Lords honour, Gods ſervice with Idolatry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doct. Whitakers</hi> in his ſecond controverſie of the Church <hi>q.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. adiudgeth the preſent Romiſh Church to be nothing elſe but <hi>a deepe pit of hereſie and errour,</hi> and thereby argueth <hi>her no wayes to be or to belong vnto the true Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Perkins</hi> in the Preface to his Reformed Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike ſaith: <hi>The whole Religion of the preſent Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church is hereticall and ſchiſmaticall, and the cup of abomination in the Whores hand, Revel.</hi> 17.4. And Doctor <hi>Abbot</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of this place in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Perkins</hi> doth iuſtifie and avow the ſame thing againſt <hi>biſhop</hi> the Papiſt.</p>
               <p>Biſhop <hi>Careton</hi> in his directions to know the true Church prooues at large that the <hi>preſent Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church holas not vnitie with the true Church, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the head, nor in the body, nor in the ſpirit, nor in the faith.</hi> If that be true ſhe is all errour, her faith is erronious.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Now I haue proved our Aſſumption againſt his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18310:22"/>exception thereto, by the authority of our Church and a cloud of her moſt learned, and renowned children, I will make the ſame good by the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of God himſelfe. But I am prevented in that by Mr. <hi>Wotton,</hi> who hath done it already in his booke called <hi>Runne from Rome,</hi> where he beginnes this poynt pag 14. num. 4. whereunto I might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Reader, as vnto a moſt pious &amp; learned au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, &amp; a worke that admitteth not any reall, eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall, or ſubſtantiall addition, but I will make bold to take out of him ſo much as belongs to this cauſe not word for word, but ſo much as will be ſutable, to the buiſineſſe.</p>
               <p>Firſt I will ſet downe how he vnfoldeth the terme and then come to his proofes of the queſtion.</p>
               <p>The word <hi>Faith</hi> importeth a ſingular thing,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devided into either members or kindes, with war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant from the Apoſtle, who ſpeakes ſo of it. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There is one faith,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>one Baptiſme, one Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator between God and man.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. In what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the <hi>Mediator is one,</hi> and <hi>Baptiſme is one,</hi> ſo <hi>Faith is once</hi> for one phraſe of ſpeech is common to them all, but they are one without diviſion into mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, or kinds: therefore ſo is faith. The thing it ſelfe ſayes no leſſe, for this word <hi>Faith,</hi> importeth a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of many ſentences made one body by a common band, namely the divine authority. For in every article a part, and in all of them together, we find the ſame authority, which draweth vs to conſent to them as true, and accordingly the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe of one, is the beleefe of all, the deniall of one, the deniall of all.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:18310:23"/>
               <p>Every Engular ſentence pronounced by the Church of Rome, as a thing revealed by God is (in this queſtion) the <hi>Romiſh faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An Article of faith is then erronious, when it <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees not with the ſacred Revelation,</hi> and this wee ſay, with warrant from the Councell of <hi>Trent Seſſ.</hi> 14. cap: 8. <hi>of the neceſsitie of Satisfaction.</hi> And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in the Decree touching <hi>the Sacrament of pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance Canon.</hi> 6. And the thing it ſelfe doth avowe the ſame: for the varying from the rule, is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry nature of error, therefore every article of faith, muſt needs be erronious that agrees not with Gods word, becauſe that word is the rule thereof. By it our faith was revealed vnto vs, and by the recorde thereof it is reſerved for vs. And ſo much for Mr. <hi>Wottons</hi> explication.</p>
               <p>We haue his proofe pag 15.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> nu. 6. thus ſet forth.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>That faith which hath a fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe and erronious founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is falſe and erronions,</item>
                  <item>But the foundation of the Romiſh ſaith is falſe and erronious:</item>
                  <item>Therefore the Romiſh faith is falſe and erronious.</item>
               </list>
               <p>In the Propoſition, two things are taken as gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. viz.
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Faith hath a foundation without it.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Different foundations cauſeth different faithes.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Both of them are cleere and evident, therefore they ſtand not in need of my proofe, if the termes be opened they will be out of queſtion. By foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation wee meane, the next and formall reaſon, why we aſſent to this or that propoſition in Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, (that is) why we iudge this predicate to bee
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18310:23"/>truly and rightly attributed to that ſubiect: now this is without the Article it ſelfe, becauſe it is no more but the authority of him that pronounceth the ſentence. In the ſecond ſentence we meane to ſay, Every diſtinct faith, followes the next and formall reaſon of our beleeving; as when wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue this or that report to be true, vpon the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of him that reports it: this is humane ſaith, becauſe it followes humane authority; and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly the faith of Turks and Heathens is accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted humane, becauſe the next reaſon of their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving is mans authority: accordingly that is Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine faith, when we eſteeme this or that ſentence to be true, becauſe God hath pronounced it. And thus haue we cleered the Propoſition.</p>
               <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Wotton</hi> prooues the Aſſumption by theſe two ſentences.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The foundation of their faith is the authority of the Paſtors of their Church. N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 7.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>This foundation of faith is falſe and erronious. N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>And this proofe is manifeſt and without excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if both theſe ſentences be true. But they are true: he prooues the firſt num. 8. by this argument</p>
               <list>
                  <item>They that haue the office to determine what is the true faith, <hi>(that is, what is revealed, &amp; what is not revealed) their authority is the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of faith.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>But the Romiſh Church, (that is, the Paſtors of their Church) hath that office.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Therefore the authority of their Church, (that is, the Paſtors of their Church) is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of their faith.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:18310:24"/>
               <p>The Propoſition needs no reliefe, for that office of ſhewing what is revealed, and what is not, is the next and formall reaſon of their beleefe, as by their doctrine and practiſe we ſhall ſee hereafter, num. 8. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The Aſſumption needes our helpe as little,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> for every man that is acquainted with their faith knowes that they giue their Church that office: yet for further explication I will ſhew the ſame by the Councel of <hi>Trent. Seſs.</hi> 4. <hi>praeterea, &amp;c.</hi> ſaith.</p>
               <q>It is the office of the Church to iudge of the true meaning and ſenſe of the Scriptures.</q>
               <p>By <hi>Church,</hi> they vnderſtand the Paſtors of the Church, and we know it by their practiſe, and the Iudgement of their learned. No man inioyeth a ſhare in the voice of deciding Iudgement in any Councel, but their Biſhops, who onely according to them are the Paſtors of the Church.</p>
               <p>By <hi>Iudging,</hi> is meant an inforcing power, compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling their ſentence to be obeyed and received.</p>
               <p>By <hi>ſenſe of the Scriptures,</hi> is vnderſtood every Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle or ſentence of faith, for an Article of faith is a ſentence held according to the true ſenſe of Gods word.</p>
               <p>By <hi>Scriptures,</hi> they vnderſtand every particular ſentence contained in the Scriptures, for if they meant ſome places onely, there could be no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty in this decree, becauſe they doe not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the particular places ſubiected to the Churches ſentence; and when they ſubiect the ſenſe of the Scriptures vnto the Churches Iudgement, they would haue vs beleeue, that the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18310:24"/>Church muſt tell vs which be the Scriptures, and which be not, elſe we can haue no divine faith of them: for reaſon tells vs they muſt haue autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in all points of faith, or none at all.</p>
               <p>This decree of the Councel thus vnderſtood,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> is followed by all their Divines, and <hi>Suarez</hi> giues it vs in this one ſentence.</p>
               <q>A generall Councell in which the Pope is preſent, either in his owne perſon, or by his Legats, and confirmed by the Pope, is an infallible rule of Faith. And this is a matter of Faith. <hi>De Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, &amp;c. Tracta. 1. Diſp. 5. Sect. 7. No. 6. &amp; 9.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bellarmine</hi> delivereth the ſelfe ſame matter in a moſt ample &amp; large manner in divers places in his third booke of Gods word, and I will report them in order as they ſtand, and thus he begins, <hi>Cap.</hi> 3. <hi>Tota igitur.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <p>The Church, (that is) the Pope, with his Councell of other Paſtors, is the Iudge of the true ſenſe of the Scriptures, in which all Catholikes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and the Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> hath it expreſly <hi>Seſſ. 4.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is committed ſingularly to <hi>Peter,</hi> and his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours, that they ſhould teach all men what is to be held concerning the doctrine of Faith. <hi>Cap. 5. Ex his, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Councels and Popes execute the office of a Iudge, committed to them by God, a Iudge deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereth his ſentence as a thing that neceſſarily muſt be followed. <hi>Cap. 10. Reſpond. aliud eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:18310:25"/>
                  <p>Chriſtians are bound to receiue the doctrine of the Church, when it ſetteth forth the matters of faith, and not to doubt whether thoſe things be ſo or not, <hi>Cap. 10. ſept. argumentum.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>Hitherto he ſetteth forth the matter in groſſe,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> and not vnfoulded, wherefore we muſt ſeeke for that alſo, and we ſhall finde the ſame in the ſaid 10. Chapter, and firſt he giveth vs a reaſon why the Church ſhould haue this office committed to her in theſe words.</p>
               <q>The Scripture for it ſelfe needs not the witneſſe of men, for it is moſt true in it ſelfe whether it be vnderſtood or not: but for our ſake it needs the witneſſe of the Church, becauſe otherwiſe we are not certaine what bookes are ſacred and divine, or what is the true and proper meaning. <hi>Cap. 10. Reſpondeo Chriſtus.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>Hitherto wee finde theſe authors concurring with the Councell in the ſenſe aforeſaid, and thereby our Aſſumption at num. 7. is confirmed, wherein we ſay, <hi>Their Church, (that is, the Paſtors of their Church) hath an office to determine which is the true faith, (that is) what is revealed, and what is not revealed:</hi> and we muſt know that their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is not a private opinion, but the faith of their Church. <hi>Suarez</hi> ſaith ſo expreſly in the place alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and the thing it ſelfe doth ſay no leſſe of them both, for they agree with the Councell, and all on their ſide agree with them; none of theirs doe deny what they affirme. If any man think not ſo, he muſt ſhew the contrary, which yet I never found. Wherefore we need not doubt of the concluſion,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18310:25"/>wherein we maintaine, <hi>That their Church is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of their faith,</hi> being the thing we vndertooke to prooue, num. 7.</p>
               <p>Though this be enough to manifeſt the matter,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> yet I will adde ſome other proofe from the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their Church to iuſtifie the ſame concluſion, becauſe I would haue the thing made eaſie to our vnderſtanding as well as proved to be true by force of argument. Now <hi>Bellarmine</hi> doth all this in moſt plaine and evident manner in the place follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <q>The word of God delivered by the Prophets and Apoſtles is the firſt foundation of our faith, for therefore we beleeve whatſoever we beleeue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God hath revealed it by his Prophets and Apoſtles; but wee adde, that beſides this firſt foundation there is another ſecondary founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion needfull, to wit, the teſtimony of the Church, for we know not certainly what God hath revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, but by the teſtimony of the Church. Therefore our faith cleaveth to Chriſt the firſt, truth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealing thoſe myſteries as to the firſt foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: It cleaves alſo to <hi>Peter,</hi> that is, to the Pope, propounding and expounding theſe myſteries, as to a ſecond foundation. <hi>Cap. 10. Reſpondeo ad hoc.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>If any man deſire to ſee this precept manifeſted by practiſe, he does that alſo after this ſort.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> 
               </p>
               <q>
                  <p>Wee are to know that a Propoſition or Article of faith is concluded in ſuch a Syllogiſme as this.</p>
                  <p>Whatſoever God hath revealed is true.</p>
                  <p>But this God hath revealed.</p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:18310:26"/>
                  <p>Therefore this is true.</p>
                  <p>Of the firſt of theſe Propoſitions no man makes any queſtion.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond is held for certaine truth amongſt all Catholiks, for it is grounded vpon the teſtrmony of the Church, Cap. <hi>10.</hi> Reſpondeo verbum.</p>
               </q>
               <p>To conclude, I will report another teſtimony of his, whereby the whole frame of this building is brought to perfection, and for that end thus he writeth.</p>
               <q>A precept of faith is to be prooued foure wayes. <hi>1.</hi> By expreſſe teſtimony of Scripture with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the Church. <hi>2.</hi> By euident deducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on out of expreſſe Scripture, with a declaration of the Church being added thereunto. <hi>3.</hi> Out of Gods word, not written by the Apoſtles, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from hand to hand. <hi>4.</hi> By eutdent deduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion out of the word of God, deliuered from hand to hand. <hi>De Purga. lib. 1. cap. 15. Haec ſive.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>Neither is this doctrine <hi>Bellarmines</hi> fancy, but it is the Romiſh faith, for it is warranted by the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of all the learned in that Church, and the Decree of the <hi>Trent</hi> Councell, already recited n. 8. for when it giues the <hi>Church the office to Iudge of the ſenſe of the Scriptures,</hi> it grants that the Scriptures are in being already, and therefore that they are the revealers of the Sacred verities, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the <hi>firſt foundation</hi> of our faith. When it ſubiecteth the ſenſe onely of the Scriptures to the iudgement of the Church, it giues the Church au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, to propound, expound, and apply the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18310:26"/>and therefore it makes the Church a <hi>ſecond foundation,</hi> and no more.</p>
               <p>By this time I hope it is evident enough,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> that the authority of the Church is the foundation, that is, the next and formall reaſon of their faith and beleeving, and that is the thing wee ſeeke for.</p>
               <p>Now we ſhould prooue,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> that this foundation of their Faith is falſe and erronious, for that is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thing propounded in this chapter num. 7. But I will ſpare that labour at this time, becauſe none of ours as I conceiue, will call it into queſtion, beſides, if any do. Mr. <hi>Wotton</hi> in the book recited even now, hath made it manifeſt againſt all oppoſers, pag. 21. num. 5. &amp;c. If therefore any man deſires to ſee it, I referre him thither, becauſe it fitteth not this buſineſſe to tranſcribe it. And thus much may ſuffice in proofe of our Aſſumption propounded cap. 3. num. 1.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 5. Defendeth this ſentence, <hi>The Romiſh faith is erronius.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> BOth our opponents are mightily gravelled with this ſentence, and all ſuch as hold it; wherefore in both their Epiſtles Dedicatory they
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:18310:27"/>propound it, and blame it, as a thorne in their eyes that may not be indured.</p>
               <p>Our opponent <hi>B.</hi> diſputeth againſt this at large: but (according as I haue done before ſo will I doe now) his long and tedious diſcourſe ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted into a narrow roome, leaſt the reader be wearied with the length, and puſled with the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: yet ſtill his owne words and true intent ſhalbe followed.</p>
               <p>Thus then he ſayes.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>In the Church of Rome is ſome good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>They teach well touching the Trinity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>The</hi> Dominicans <hi>maintaine Gods free grace, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt mans freewill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>Much good is in the twelue bookes of</hi> Alvarez, <hi>and in the interpretations and Commentaries of</hi> Maldonat, Lorynus, <hi>and the reſt of the</hi> Ieſuites. pag 90.</p>
               <p n="5">5 <hi>Wee agree on both ſides in theſe poynts following.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>That the bookes of the old Teſtament written in Hebrew are Canonicall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>That we are inſtified by faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>That God hath made heaven and hell for mens ſoules after death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>That God may be worſhipped in Spirit without an Image</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5 <hi>That wee are to pray vnto God by Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6 <hi>That there be two Sacraments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7 <hi>That Chriſt is really received in the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8 <hi>That Chriſt hath made one oblation of himſelfe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Croſſe for the redemption and ſatisfaction for the ſinnes of the whole world,</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:18310:27"/>9 <hi>Vnder the Papacy is much good, nay all, yea the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry kernell of Chriſtianity pag.</hi> 39. 40. 41.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, our Opponent <hi>C. pag.</hi> 4. and 5.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> blames the man <hi>that affirmes without pooofe,</hi> and makes it a Law, that <hi>ſuch an affirmation is as ſoone denyed as made.</hi> This is the caſe of this opponent. He telleth vs a tale of their agreement with vs in diverſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, but he alledgeth no author, book, or chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, whereby we may try, whether he ſayes true or not; <hi>if then we deny, that they and wee doe thus agree, all his building falls to the ground,</hi> according to his partners ſentence, pag 4. Thus ſoundly he anſwers to the thing that doth moſt vrge him, but for this time I am content to ſay, they and we doe thus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, yet behold his caſe from himſelfe <hi>pag.</hi> 82. <hi>Wee heare of a great cry and little woll:</hi> &amp; <hi>pag.</hi> 83. of a man <hi>whoſe skill in Logick was ſo good, that hee prooued what was granted, and being granted, was to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</hi> Now I commend him for ſo doing, becauſe I perceiue he ſpake the very truth, but himſelfe gaines nothing thereby, for of him it is verified to the full, and that in this preſent anſwer, wherein he ſpends the greateſt part of 7 pages before he ends it, viz. 39. 40. 41. 86. 87. 90. 91. yet ten words had ſerved the turn, as well as all this ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. If he had ſaid no more but thus: <hi>The Romiſh Church agrees with vs in many divine ſentences,</hi> he had beene as neere his purpoſe as now: therefore <hi>we haue a great cry and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle woll.</hi> If he reply that all the reſt prooues that ſentence, I reioynd, I am content it ſhall be ſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that ſhewes his great skill in Logick, for then he prooues the thing that none will deny, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:18310:28"/>granted, ſerues not his purpoſe, which none will doe, but the good Logician which his part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner deſcribeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> If we frame this anſwer with the preſent queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on according to art, and all the parts thereof be true, then it is to the purpoſe, elſe not; thus then it muſt be framed.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>They that agree with vs in the particulars recited, their faith is not erronious.</item>
                  <item>But the Romiſh Church agrees with vs in the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars recited.</item>
                  <item>Therefore their faith is not erronious.</item>
               </list>
               <p>But no part of this Argument is good. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is not true: and why may I not ſay ſo, ſeeing in it ſelfe, and by it ſelfe, it is not manifeſt, neither does he offer any proofe for it; and now I haue denied it, his whole building is come to ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, according to his partners-rule, pag. 4. even now recited.</p>
               <p>To the Propoſition I anſwer,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> that it preſumes, that the forenamed Articles are true, and every way the ſame thing with the Romiſh faith, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon giues one ſtate or condition to thoſe Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and that faith, attributing truth to the ſecond, from the truth of the firſt. Theſe Articles in ſome ſenſe are true, and ſo farre the Propoſition is true alſo: but thoſe Articles and the Romiſh faith are not the ſame thing: but this extends further then them, and himſelfe, even he that now anſweres be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing iudge, pag. 40. He writes thus: <hi>To the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures they adde Traditions, to the Hebrew Canon the Apocrypha, to faith workes, to Heaven and Hell Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:18310:28"/>and ſo forth in the reſt:</hi> whereupon his Propoſition beggs the queſtion, and therefore it hath no force to inferre the concluſion. His part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <hi>C.</hi> pag. 2. cannot abide <hi>beggery,</hi> but this doth loue it weele; but in the meane time he is a good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Diſputer, that can prooue nothing, vnleſſe we grant him what himſelfe denies: this is enough to ſatisfie this Argument, becauſe this feigned ſurmiſe is the firſt and originall foundation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. But out of our ſtore of exceptions hereunto for this time, we will forgiue him this fault, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the reſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> We agree with the Romiſh Church in the recited Articles, as they are Propoſitions, (that is) they and we pronounce the ſame thing as true, &amp; ſo farr the Aſſumption is granted; but the Propoſition is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, becauſe faith and a true Propoſition really differs: the one is no more but a ſubiect, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate, rightly ioyned together, whereupon truth in all Propoſitions is the ſame, namely the adequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the thing and the Propoſition: but in faith there is alſo the foundation wherevpon wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, from whence it comes to paſſe, that faith is of different kindes, ſome divine, and ſome hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, as I haue ſhewed.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> In the recited Articles wee agree not with the Romiſh, as they are Articles of faith: For in them wee doe really and eſſentially differ. They pronounce them to bee true, vpon the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of their Church, which is (indeed) humane, we vpon the authority of Chriſt the Revealer, which by joynt conſent is divine. Theſe things being
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18310:29"/>true, (as they are moſt true) his Aſſumption at num. 4. cannot be true, and conſequently, there is no meanes to excuſe the Rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh faith from error; nor cauſe to giue her the name, and nature of a true Church: which is the thing we ſeeke for.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 6. Defendeth this ſentence: <hi>The faith of the Church is not right and pure, falſe and erronious together:</hi> viz. in different Articles.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> WE muſt now goe back againe to the reſt of opponent <hi>B.</hi> his anſwere left vnſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, in cap. 3. num. 8. The firſt branch whereof (we are now to deale withall) hath theſe words.</p>
               <q>The doctrine of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, taught purely without mixture of errour, is not ſo eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall to the true Church, that ſo ſoone as an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound doctrine is mingled with the truth of Gods word, and the Sacraments vnduely admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred, that which was a Church ſhould ceaſe to be one.</q>
               <p>In theſe words, this ſentence is implied:
<q>The faith of the Church, may be right and true, falſe and erronious together: <hi>viz. in different Articles.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:18310:29"/>
               <p>And he does expreſſely avouch the ſame in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers paſſages of his booke; viz.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>The preſent Church of Rome, is corrupted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, yet hath the true eſſence of a Church: pag. <hi>30.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Church of Rome hath a religion more after <hi>Homer,</hi> then after the Scriptures, and yet hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth fundamentall truth: pag. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the Popes Arithmetick, Articles of faith are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: pag. <hi>39.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Such affirmatiues of ours, as concerne the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Faith, are profeſſed by the Church of Rome: pag: <hi>41.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>And nothing is more frequent with him, then words to this effect.</p>
               <q>The Church of Rome, (that is all thoſe which ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in that religion make vp one body or ſocietie) is not <hi>Babylon</hi> in the Revelation: but, that <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> is a faction in that Church: pag. <hi>100.</hi> The Papacy is not the Church: but the diſeaſe of the Church. The Papacy is in the Church, as an accident in the ſubiect: we muſt diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Church, and the Papacy: pag. <hi>28, 29.</hi> Wee haue learned to diſtinguiſh betwixt the Church, and the great Whore in the Church: we haue communion with the Church, wee ſeperate from <hi>Babylon:</hi> pag. <hi>101.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>This we deny,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and will maintaine the contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, (to wit) <hi>The faith of the Church, is not right and true, falſe and erronious together:</hi> viz. in diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Articles. But, <hi>If ſome Articles of Faith be falſe and erronious, then the Faith of the Church it falſe and erronious.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:18310:30"/>
               <p>I will not now giue reaſon of this denyall: but deferr the ſame till we come to the 7. Chap. where it ſhall be diſputed ſo much as is requiſite.</p>
               <p>He brings proofe for his opinion,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> in the words which immediately follow in the foreſaid Cap. 3. n. 8. I will firſt diſpoſe them according to Art, and then frame my anſwer, as ſhall be needfull.</p>
               <p>Thus then he diſputes:
<q>
                     <p>If the Faith of the Church cannot be true, and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronious together, then where error in faith is, there cannot be a true Church.</p>
                     <p>But where error in faith is, there may bee a true Church: for firſt, our Church thinks ſo, Article <hi>19.</hi> according to <hi>Mr. Rogers,</hi> in his Commentary vpon the place, Propo. <hi>8.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <hi>2</hi> The children of Iſraell did abide many dayes without a Sacrifice and Ephod, &amp;c. <hi>Hoſea 3.4.</hi> and without Circumciſion, the ſpace of <hi>40.</hi> yeares: <hi>Ioſh: 5.6.</hi> yet then were they the Church of God.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <hi>3</hi> The word and Sacraments may be corrupted, as in the times of blindneſſe, and ſuperſtition; or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termitted as in perſecution.</p>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> the conſequence of the Propoſition we grant, as very neceſſary: But the Aſſumption is falſe. Wee ſay, that, errour in faith, and the Church are incompatible: and, it is the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Church already alledged out of the Homily.</p>
               <p>To all his proofes ioyntly, I anſwere: They are farr to weake to vphold this waighty matter, if this aſſumption be not true, then his whole cauſe falles to the ground. Himſelfe confeſſeth (as wee haue
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:18310:30"/>heard) that the preſent Romiſh Church is guiltie of hereſy; and, therefore can be no true Church, vnleſſe error in faith may be in the Church: For herefie (at leaſt) comprehends error in faith. Wherefore it ſtood him vpon to gather his witts, and vnite his forces together, to ſtrengthen and mainteyne this buſineſſe: we looked for preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant proofe out of Gods word, (for doubtleſſe) if this were true, we ſhould find a manifeſt record for it: becauſe God hath not left matters of this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance for man to grope, and gueſſe at. So lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and wiſe was the Lord, when he appoynted the meanes of mans ſalvation. But loe, no ſuch thing is tendred, and therefore wee may conclude, no ſuch thing is in being, and conſequently, wee may ſet downe our reſt and ſay, doubtleſſe the faith of the true Church cannot be ſtained with error: yet that the miſery of this cauſe may the better ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, I will vncover the skirts of all his proofes, in perticular, and ſingle out the one from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The authority of our Church prevaileth much with me, ſo as, that alone would ſilence my tongue, and ſuſpend my iudgement: but it will doe little good to this opponent <hi>B.</hi> for he that ſlighteth, yea reiecteth, nay diſputeth againſt her doctrine in things ſupreame, muſt not craue her ayde in things belonging to the mean: and thus ſtands it with this opponent, who mainteynes the cheife queſtion in this buſineſſe againſt her, and at this inſtant, labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth all he can, to refell the Propoſition of her ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument. But how may it appeare, that our <hi>Church</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:18310:31"/>makes for him? He brings nothing but the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Mr. <hi>Rogers,</hi> and that is no greater then his owne, and conſequently thus he ſayes, our Church thought ſo, becauſe I ſay ſhe did thinke ſo: but what if our Church and this opponent ſayes ſhee thought not ſo, then (I hope) the matter thus farr, will be at an end.</p>
               <p>From this <hi>Opponent</hi> I argue thus. He that ſaith all Gods revealed truth vniuerſally, eſſentially, and reciprically belongs to the Church, frees the faith of the Church from error. But this opponent doth ſo, (for thus he writes <hi>pag</hi> 13. <hi>The true Church is a company of men profeſsing Gods revealed truth</hi>) now, in this ſentence, he makes all Gods revealed truth to belong to the Church vniuerſally, eſſentially, and reciprically: becauſe 1. The words themſelues (in the common vſe of men) doe lye ſo. 2. According to <hi>Ariſtotle: Poſter: lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap:</hi> 44 &amp; 33. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>Top. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap:</hi> 1. <hi>Thom.</hi> 2. <hi>diſt.</hi> 27. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>art.</hi> 2. <hi>ad</hi> 9<hi rend="sup">m</hi>. <hi>Aliaco. queſt. de reſumpt. lit q Richardus de Trin. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. <hi>fol.</hi> 108. Every exact or perfite definition does ſo: but this Authors ſentence alledged, is an exact definition: pag. 13. Therefore this opponent frees the faith of the Church from error, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently (according to him) our Church doth ſo too: for ſhee hath defined the Church, art. 19. iuſt as he hath done in the ſentence we alledged.</p>
               <p>If art. 19.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> ſubiecteth the faith of the Church vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to error, then wee muſt reade it thus. <hi>The viſible Church is a Congregation, in which ſome part of the pure word of God is preached, and the Sacraments in ſome things be only adminiſtred.</hi> But art. 19. muſt not
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:18310:31"/>be ſo read, leaſt the words of the Article (them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues) be perverted, and ſome man ſay, the avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of diverſities of opinions, and eſtabliſhing of conſent touching true religion, was not thereby in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended: contrary vnto the proteſtation of our Church in the title to all the Articles in generall. Therefore Art. 19. ſubiecteth not the faith of the Church vnto errour.</p>
               <p>His ſecond proofe lyeth thus:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>The Iſraelites wanted Sacrifice and Circumciſion:</l>
                     <l>Therefore the faith of the Church is ſubiect to errour.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwere, this geere hangs not together, ſo well as <hi>Harp</hi> and <hi>Harrow;</hi> for they ſound alike in ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, becauſe both of them begin with a letter: but here is nothing like: The lewes Church was an Infant, and not eſtabliſhed: Chriſts Church (whereof we ſpeak) is of ripe age, and full growth. Their Sacrifice, Ephod, and Circumciſion, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing like to the faith of Chriſts Church. Their want of Sacrifice, Ephod, and Circumciſion, is a meere privation, and a not being: Errour in faith is ſome poſition, for it comprehendeth an incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable Iudgement, or opinion.</p>
               <p>His third and laſt proofe ſtands on this faſhion.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> 
               </p>
               <q>
                  <p>The word and Sacraments may be corrupted in the time of blindneſſe, and ſuperſtition, or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted as in the the time of perſecution.</p>
                  <p>Therefore the faith of the Church is ſubiect to errour.</p>
               </q>
               <p>I anſwer: the farther the worſe, he muſt vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the word and Sacraments to be every way
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18310:32"/>the ſame thing with the faith of the Church; ſo alſo he muſt vnderſtand the termes, <hi>corrupted,</hi> and <hi>intermitted,</hi> to be every way the ſame with theſe termes, <hi>ſubiect to errour:</hi> elſe, here is not the leaſt ſhew of conſequence: but how he will doe that, I doe not yet ſee, and I preſume I never ſhall: hee brings no proofes for the Antecedent, therefore at the beſt, we haue but his owne word.</p>
               <p>The laſt argument,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> (which I can finde) belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto this matter, is in the Opponent <hi>B.</hi> his Engliſh Epiſtle, a little after the beginning, in theſe words:
<q>If an Heretick were put to death for his Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an profeſsion ſake, wee could not deny him the name of a Martyr.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And we may apply it to the preſent purpoſe in this forme.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Every Martyr is a member of the true Church.</item>
                  <item>Some Heretick is a Martyr, viz. ſuch a one as ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers death for his Chriſtian profeſsion ſake.</item>
                  <item>Therefore ſome Heretick is a member of the true Church, and conſequently, the faith of the Church may be true and falſe together.</item>
               </list>
               <p>I anſwer: Every Martyr in the ſenſe of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, <hi>Revel.</hi> 20.4. is a member of the true Church; and ſo farre the Propoſition is true: but the Aſſumption is falſe, no Heretick is or can be ſuch a Martyr. This Opponent may preſume it, and does; but prooue it, he neither does, nor can: becauſe the ſame holy Ghoſt willeth vs, <hi>to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void an Heretick as a party condemned of his owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience:</hi> Tit. 3.10. (and therefore of God who is
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:18310:32"/>greater then the heart. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.21.) If God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes an heretick, he eſteemes him not a Martyr. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 20.4. For ſuch Martyrs are commended and ſaved. <hi>Revel.</hi> 20.4. If this opponent takes the word <hi>Martyr</hi> otherwiſe then God does, I deny the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and ſay, He that is no Martyr of Gods, is no member of the true Church, notwithſtanding his name and tittle of Martyrdome. In this ſence I grant the Aſſumption, namely, ſome heretick may bee a Martyr in the account of man, but not of God.</p>
               <p>The proofe of his Aſſumption ſuppoſeth,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> that an heretick may profeſſe Chriſtianity, and I ſay ſo too. If he meanes that he may ſo profeſſe, according to humane faith, and naturall reaſon, then we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed; becauſe hereſie is a worke of the fleſh, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.20. and is exerciſed about the Chriſtian faith, importing errour in faith: but then his Aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is vnprooved, becauſe, no man that is ſuch a Chriſtian, can be a Martyr, <hi>Revel.</hi> 20.4. for Gods Martyrs goe to heaven, but ſo does not ſuch Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: fleſh and blood inherit not the Kingdome of heaven, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.50.</p>
               <p>If he thinks,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> ſome hereticks profeſſe Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, (that is ſalvation by Chriſt) according vnto di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine faith, he begs the queſtion, viz. That the faith of the Church may be true and falſe, right and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronious, orthodox and hereticall together: which we deny, and he vndertakes (by this very Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) to prooue: O acute! ô admirable Diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter! Bring the concluſion to prooue the concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who would deſire better? Doubtleſſe his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorick,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:18310:33"/>not his Logick, wrought now; becauſe, he prefers that (for diſputation) before this: pag. 80, 81. But now, all the fat is in the fire: he that begs the queſtion prooues nothing, if <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> may be Iudge, <hi>Top. l.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. and this begging, of all others, is the moſt beggerly: for, it is a womans reaſon, they vſe to ſay, It is ſo, becauſe it is ſo: and iuſt ſo does he. This is anſwere enough for ſuch petty trifles, and thus are we come to an end of all that which Opponent <hi>B.</hi> hath to ſay againſt the Propoſition of our Churches Argument, Cap. 3. num. 1. and therewithall I haue finiſhed a full de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of that whole Argument: The Reader muſt now iudge whether the Mother or the rebellious childe hath the better.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 7. Containeth a ſecond proofe, that <hi>[The Romiſh faith is falſe and erronious.]</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Mr.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <hi>Wotton</hi> hath ſaved me a labour in this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage alſo, pag. 46. hee bringeth this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>If ſome Articles of the Romiſh faith be falſe and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronious, then the Romiſh faith is falſe and erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious.</item>
                  <item>But ſome Articles of the Romiſh faith be falſe and erronious.</item>
                  <item>Therefore the Romiſh faith is falſe and erronious.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Perhaps I may ſeeme vnto ſome to argue very
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:18310:33"/>looſely, becauſe it is a ruled caſe, ſome parts can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not argue the whole, becauſe all the parts toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe make vp the whole, and are adequate thereunto. If ſome parts be wanting, the whole is not obtained: from whence it falls out, the ſtate, condition, and denomination, of ſome parts alone, doe not belong to the whole.</p>
               <p>I reply, ſuch a man miſtakes this reaſon:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> I doe not argue the whole to be ſo, becauſe ſome parts are ſo, the reſt being free: but I prooue the whole is to be held erronious, becauſe there is an infection of errour in the whole.</p>
               <p>If any man deſire to know how errour in ſome Articles onely is errour in the whole faith: I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, he may ſatisfie himſelfe in that demand, cap. 4. num. 5. where it is prooved, That <hi>Faith is ſuch an vnite, and continued thing, that though it is made of many ingredients, yet it admitteth no diviſion into members, or kindes.</hi> Now, this being true, (as it is moſt true) then the faith of the Church can no wayes be ſaid to be erronious in any one Article, but preſently the whole is erronious.</p>
               <p>This Argument and manner of reaſoning,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> is ſhadowed out in a leprous man, who is accounted and dealt withall as wholly leprous, though the ſeat of the diſeaſe be in the fleſh onely: the reaſon is, becauſe, though in a divided ſenſe, and in our apprehenſion, man conſiſteth, and is compounded of, diſtinct beings, viz. ſoule and body, fleſh and ſpirit, yet take him an individuall man, he is ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacted, that he is made one Hypoſtecis, or conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued ſubſiſtency, limited by one terme onely.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:18310:34"/>Wherefore when the Prieſt in <hi>Moſes</hi> Law gaue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of a leprous man, the whole man was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended vnder that ſentence, If a leprous man was ſhut out of the hoſt, the whole man, (not ſome part onely) was thruſt out: and this was not againſt reaſon, for the ſoule gaue life, ſenſe, and vigitation to the fleſh, and thereby it became ſubiect to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſe and defection, and conſequently the ſoule was indeed leprous, though by reflection, and at ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond hand: ſo is it with the Chriſtian faith, errour may be ſeated only in ſome Articles, yet the whole ſtand infected therewith; becauſe the foundation of faith, which is the ſoule thereof, runs through the whole, as one continued ſtreame without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſſion, diſtinction, or limitation; by reaſon whereof, if ſome Articles onely be charged with errour, the foundation of faith cannot be free, if that be infected, the whole faith is ſubiect thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; becauſe, every Article or Propoſition becomes an Article of faith by the force and efficacy of that foundation.</p>
               <p>I conceiue by this time that the Propoſition of this Argument is ſufficiently prooved,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and explai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: ſo as every man will beleeue, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it, and, accordingly, I may content my ſelfe, and ſaue all further labour: yet becauſe the Reader ſhall haue full and ample ſatisfaction, I will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed ſomewhat further.</p>
               <p>All ours doe grant the Aſſumption,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> namely, that, <hi>ſome Articles of the Romiſh faith be erronious:</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt both our Opponents are laviſh e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in words of that kinde, calling that Church
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:18310:34"/>(ſo farre as their faith is erronious) <hi>Babell,</hi> and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall, ſo as in rigour I am not bound to anſwere further: yet becauſe our Opponent <hi>B.</hi> hath done it ſamely, and falſely, pag. 40.90.124. &amp;c. to the ſhame of his owne reading, and the <hi>ſorrow and ſhame of our whole Nation,</hi> if I may ſpeake in his partners language, pag. 22. To mend the matter, and for the Readers ſake, I will proceed and ſhew, that ſome Articles of their faith be erronious, by aſſigning the particulars which are ſo faulty, that it may be knowne we doe them no wrong, when we charge them in that manner: beſides this, every lover of truth, may the better be directed to ſever truth from falſhood: for that purpoſe I frame this Argument.</p>
               <p>All the ſucceeding Articles are erronious, viz.</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>The ſaving truth taught by Chriſt, and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, is conteined alſo, in vnwritten Traditions.</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell Trent, Seſſ. 4.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Originall ſinne is an vneleanneſſe within mans ſoule, and is a ſin which is the death of the ſoule.</hi> Seſſ. 5. Decret. 2. &amp; 3.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Grace doth take away, whatſoever hath the true, and proper nature of ſinne.</hi> Seſſ. 5. Decret. 5.</p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>Concupiſcence in the regenerate, is not truly, and properly ſinne.</hi> Seſſ. 5. Decret. 5.</p>
               <p n="5">5 <hi>Hee that receiveth the inſpiration of grace, can [actually] reiect the ſame, and [actually] diſſent therefrom, if he will.</hi> Seſſ. 6. Cap. 5. Can. 4.</p>
               <p n="6">6 <hi>The onely formall cauſe of Iuſtification, is Iuſtice inherent.</hi> Seſſ. 6. Cap. 7.</p>
               <p n="7">7 <hi>Sinne is mortall and veniall.</hi> Cap. 11. &amp; 14.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:18310:35"/>8 <hi>The iuſt, in ſome actions, doe not ſinne venially.</hi> Cap. 11.</p>
               <p n="9">9 <hi>By every mortall ſin, a man falleth away from the grace of Iuſtification, which he had receiued.</hi> cap. 14.15.</p>
               <p n="10">10 <hi>Gods Commandements are not impoſsible to bee kept by him that is iuſtified.</hi> Seſſ. 6. Cap. 11.</p>
               <p n="11">11 <hi>The grace of iuſtification is beſtowed vpon them, alſo, which are not preaeſtinate.</hi> Seſſ. 6. Can: 17.</p>
               <p n="12">12 <hi>The whole temporall puniſhment, is not alwayes remitted together with the fault.</hi> Seſſ: 6. Cap. 14. and Can. 30: Seſſ. 14. Cap. 8. Can. 12.</p>
               <p n="13">13 <hi>The works which be done in God, doe, for the ſtate of this life, fully ſatisfie the Law.</hi> Seſſ. 6. Cap. 16.</p>
               <p n="14">14 <hi>The iuſt, in ſome actions, ſinne not at all: and in no action doe they deſerue eternall puniſhment.</hi> Seſſ. 6. Cap. 11.</p>
               <p n="15">15 <hi>The good works of the iuſt are their merits.</hi> Seſſ. 6. Cap. 16. Can. 32.</p>
               <p n="16">16 <hi>The Iuſtified, by their good works, do truely me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit the obtayning of eternall life it ſelfe</hi> Seſſ. 6. Can. 32.</p>
               <p n="17">17 <hi>It is no ſinne to worke in the intuition of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi> Seſſ. 6. Cap. 11. Can. 31.</p>
               <p n="18">18 <hi>The Images of Chriſt, the Virgine Mary, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Saints.</hi> 1. <hi>Are to be had, and kept, cheifely in Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</hi> 2. <hi>Due honour, and worſhip, is to be giuen vnto them.</hi> 3. <hi>Are of Sacred vſe, and yeeld much fruit.</hi> Seſſ: 25: Decret: de invocat.</p>
               <p n="19">19 <hi>The honour which we yeeld vnto Images, is refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto the thing which they repreſent, &amp; whoſe like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes they beare.</hi> Seſſ. 25.</p>
               <p n="20">20 <hi>Worſhip and honour is due to be giuen, to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes of Saints departed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="21">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:18310:35"/>21 <hi>The Monuments, and memories of the Saints de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, are to be frequented, and honoured.</hi> Seſſ: 25.</p>
               <p n="22">22 <hi>Feaſt dayes are to be kept, in honour and celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Saints, and for viſiting their Reliques.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="23">23 <hi>By viſiting the Reliques of Saints, we obtayne their help.</hi> Seſſ. 25.</p>
               <p n="24">24 <hi>Prayers are to be made, for the faithfull departed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="25">25 <hi>The Saints that raigne with Chriſt, and enioy eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall felicity in heaven,</hi> 1 <hi>are to be called vpon.</hi> 2 <hi>they pray for vs, even, ſingular men.</hi> 3 <hi>It is profitable for vs, to fly to their prayers, help, and furtherance for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifites to be receiued from God.</hi> Seſſ. 25.</p>
               <p n="26">26 <hi>There is a Purgatorie.</hi> Seſſ. 25.</p>
               <p n="27">27 <hi>Some temporall puniſhment remayneth to be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied for in purgatory, before the way to heauen can bee opened.</hi> Seſſ. 6. Can. 30,</p>
               <p n="28">28 <hi>The power of granting Indulgences was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Chriſt to the Church, and the vſe of them is help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to Chriſtian people.</hi> Seſſ. 25. Decret. de Indul.</p>
               <p n="29">29 <hi>The whole choiſe of meates ſerueth vnto the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification of the fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="30">30 <hi>The deuout celebration of feaſt dayes, cauſeth the increaſe of piety.</hi> Seſſ. 25. Decret: de delectu.</p>
               <p n="31">31 <hi>The Sacrifice of the Maſſ, prayers, almes giuing, are ſuffrages of the faithfull, that are aliue, for other faithfull that are dead.</hi> Seſſ: 25. Decret: de Purga.</p>
               <p n="32">32 <hi>The Sacraments of the new Teſtament, are neither more, nor fewer then ſeven: to wit,</hi> 1 <hi>Baptiſme.</hi> 2 <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation.</hi> 3 <hi>The Lords Supper.</hi> 4 <hi>Pennance.</hi> 5 <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame Vnction.</hi> 6 <hi>Ordination.</hi> 7 <hi>Matrimony. And every one of theſe, is truely and properly a Sacrament.</hi> Seſſ: 7: Can. 1.</p>
               <p n="33">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:18310:36"/>33 <hi>The Sacraments of the New Teſtament contayne the things they ſignifi, and beſlow it vpon them which hindreth not.</hi> Can: 6. <hi>And vpon all, as much as is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyred on Gods part.</hi> Ca: 7. <hi>And that by the worke wrought:</hi> Can: 8. <hi>Baptiſme, Confirmation, and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, imprint in the ſoule, a character that cannot be blotted out:</hi> Can: 9,</p>
               <p n="34">34 <hi>After the Conſecration of the bread and wine in the Lords Supper, the Lord Ieſus Christ, true God and Man, is contained, truely, really, and ſubſtantially, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſhewes of thoſe ſenſible things.</hi> Seſſ: 13. de Sacra: Eucha: Cap: 1. Can: 1.</p>
               <p n="35">35 <hi>By the conſecration of the bread and wine, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion is made of the whole ſubſtance of the bread, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſubſtance of Chriſts body, and of the whole ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the wine, into the ſubſtance of his blood: ſo as, in that Sacrament the ſubſtance of bread and wine remaynes not together with the body and blood of Chriſt. Which converſion, is properly called tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation.</hi> Cap: 4. Can: 2.</p>
               <p n="36">36 <hi>In the Maſſe a true and proper Sacrifice is offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto God, Propitiatory, and profitable vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, alſo, beſids ſuch as receiue it, and it ought to bee offred for the quick and dead, for ſatisfaction of the puniſhment of ſinnes, and other neceſsities.</hi> Seſſ: 22. Can. 3.</p>
               <p n="37">37 <hi>The holy Euchariſt is to be reſerved in the Chancell, and carried honorably to the ſicke.</hi> Seſſ. 13. Cap. 6. <hi>To be worſhipped with a peculiar feſtiuall ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebritie, and divine worſhip; yea externall alſo: ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and publickly to be caryed about, that it may be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped by the people.</hi> Can. 6.</p>
               <p n="38">
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:18310:36"/>38 <hi>Water is to be mingled with wine in the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice that is to be offred.</hi> Seſſ. 22. Cap. 7.</p>
               <p n="39">39 <hi>No man that knowes himſelfe to be guiltie of mortall ſinne, how contrite ſoever he ſeemes to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be, may come to the holy Enchariſt without Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentall Confeſsion going before.</hi> Seſſ. 13. Cap. 7. Can. 11. <hi>that is, vnill he haue confeſſed all, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of his mortall ſinnes, and alſo thoſe circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which change the kinde of the ſinne.</hi> Seſſ. 14. Cap. 5. <hi>and that to a Prieſtan ſecret.</hi> Can. 6.7.</p>
               <p n="40">40 <hi>Our Saviour Chriſt when hee ſayd [doe this in remembrance of me] did inſtitute his Apoſtles Prieſts, and ordained that themſelues and other Prieſts ſhould offer his body, and blood:</hi> Seſſ: 22: Can. 2.</p>
               <p n="41">41 <hi>No man, vnleſſe he doth Conſecrate, is bound by Gods Law, to receiue vnder both kinds.</hi> Seſſ: 21. Cap. 1: <hi>but all ſuch muſt receiue vnder one kinde on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> Cap. 5.</p>
               <p n="42">42 <hi>Wee may make ſatisfaction to God, through Ieſus Chriſt, by temporall afflictions, layd on vs by God, and borne patiently by vs.</hi> Seſſ. 14. Cap. 9. <hi>and</hi> Can. 15.</p>
               <p n="43">43 <hi>By the Sacrament of Pennance, the grace of Inſtification which was loſt is recovered.</hi> Seſſ: 6. Cap. 14.</p>
               <p n="44">44 <hi>Matrymony contracted, not conſummated, is diſſolued by the ſolemne profeſsion of Religion, by ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther partie.</hi> Seſſ. 24. Can. 6.</p>
               <p n="45">45 <hi>Power was given to the Apoſtles, and their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſucceſſors to remit, and retaine ſinnes, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling of ſuch of the faithfull as fall after Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me.</hi> Seſſ. 14. de ſacra peniten. Cap. 1.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:18310:37"/>
               <p>But theſe are Articles of the Romiſh faith.</p>
               <p>Therefore ſome Articles of the Romiſh faith be erronious.</p>
               <p>None of ours will deny either part of this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> vnleſſe he be very ill adviſed. If any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept againſt any branch of the Propoſition, let him aſſigne the particular, and he ſhall ſee by our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweres and arguments, that it agrees not with Gods word, and therefore it is erronious.</p>
               <p>If it be anſwered ſome of theirs doe not agree to the Councell in the particulars aſſigned, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their faith is not recorded therein, and ſo our Opponent ſeemes to argue, pag. 108. and 130. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, the Antecedent is falſe, no man can name a member of their Church, that bids defiance to the authority of that Councell, nor can: for ſuch a party is accurſed by the Councell, and thereby made an heretick, and none of theirs as we finde in the decree thereof, touching the receiving and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving of the decrees of that Councell, Seſſ. 25. and the acclamation of the Fathers at the end of that Councell: whereupon we may reſt aſſured, that ſome Articles of their faith be erronious, and which they be in particular. Having hitherto diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſed the firſt principall queſtion, propounded, cap. 1. num. 1. I now deſcend to the ſecond, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I may be the more briefe; becauſe I haue inſiſted ſo long vpon the firſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:18310:37"/>
               <head>CHAP. 8. Prooveth this ſentence, <hi>No Papiſt, (as a Papiſt) can be ſaved.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis poſition ſpeakes not of ſalvation actually,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and in the event; but of the meanes and poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of attaining ſalvation by their faith.</p>
               <p>By <hi>Papiſt</hi> is meant, ſuch a man as does commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate in the Romiſh faith. So as in plaine Engliſh this ſentence ought to be pronounced thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Romiſh faith diſpoſeth or leadeth not vnto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It belongs not to vs to iudge of the event,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and hell are in the hands of God, and to ſend men thither it is a right ſo peculiar to God, that he will not account with vs for it. His ſacred Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhewes vs the way to obtaine the one, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void the other; wherefore about this may we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, and muſt: about that we doe not ſtriue, nor may: leſt we ſeeke to be <hi>wiſe</hi> beyond <hi>ſobriety,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Apoſtles rule, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.3.</p>
               <p>Thus haue we propounded the point,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foulded the ſenſe. It remaineth that in the next place wee ſee what our adverſaries ſay to it. The Opponent <hi>B.</hi> pag. 6. writeth thereof in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
               <q>The ſtate of the Church of Rome, both now and many yeares paſt, is and hath beene ſuch, that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:18310:38"/>plagues were due vnto them, even from the greateſt to the leaſt, even to all without excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as well to authours, as receivers, from the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diot, and Handicrafts man, to the Pope, and the Colledge of Cardinalls: becauſe their religion in many parts of it hath beene hereticall, and erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious for opinion and practiſe.</q>
               <p>I anſwere,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> ſo farre as theſe words doe guide vs, we muſt ſay, that this Opponent oppoſeth not vs in this point: for if their religion made them guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of, and lyable vnto puniſhment, then doubtleſſe their faith leads not to eternall life: for it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible it ſhould tend to two ends of adverſe nature: ſo as now we will take him for a friend, not as an enemy: for we think him ſo honeſt, that his heart and hand doe agree.</p>
               <p>In the next page hee layeth out the way for their eſcape from the ſaid danger of puniſhment,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> and aſſigneth <hi>Repentance to bee the meanes: namely repentance, either actuall or generall. By the firſt he would haue all ſuch to avoid that danger and be ſaved, which indeed haue builded themſelues vpon the rock, which is the foundation of the Church; though through ignorance they hold the ſame but weakly, &amp; frame ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny baſe &amp; vnſutable things therupon: but he thinks that actuall repentance is neceſſary for all knowne faults.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwere,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> he profeſſeth in his margin, that he borrowed this diſcourſe from M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Hooker,</hi> (of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe as I conceiue for his further grace) but it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailes him little. If he will be our debtor we will grant him all his writing, who will not ſay, that by repentance the greateſt ſinner may avoid hell, and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:18310:38"/>goe to heaven; ſeeing that, God hath promiſed to <hi>put all our ſinnes out of his remembrance whenſoever we repent: Ezek.</hi> 18. Yet notwithſtanding we need not feare his ſtrength in this cauſe, for two reaſons. 1. This is nothing to the preſent buſineſſe, for we enquire after the end vnto which the Romiſh faith doth tend, and he ſheweth the fruit, profit, or end of repentance: how farre then repentance, or tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning away from the Popiſh faith is different, or diſtant from the Popiſh faith, ſo farre is hee wide from the cauſe in hand. 2. This diſcourſe, makes ſtrongly for our aſſertion, thus. If a man muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of the Popiſh religion, that is he muſt turne himſelfe from it, before he can avoid hell, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine heaven, then doubtleſſe the Romiſh faith leads not to heaven: for the way thither ſtands not in need of repentance. Now, let who elſe will grace his anſwere, ſeeing the more glory it hath, the more glorious is our cauſe, which is ſo ſtrongly confirmed by it.</p>
               <p>His partner Opponent <hi>C.</hi> rambleth about this matter, and ſcattereth (in divers places) ſome words tending to the ſame purpoſe: but I will not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble my ſelfe and the Reader with them, onely it is meet that we obſerue, (in his Epiſtle Dedicatory) that he maketh the point now in hand one of thoſe whereat he trembles when he does but heare it. If there be any cauſe why, it will ſhew it ſelfe by his arguments and anſweres for it, if he be naked in them, we may conclude that he feares without a cauſe, and <hi>runnes when none purſues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Enough hath bin ſaid already, to driue this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:18310:39"/>to the head: we haue proved that the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh faith</hi> is erronious: by arguments that are not, nor can be refelled, and who would require more, to argue her faith to be vnable, and altogether vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, to lead a man to heaven? Can an erronious faith ſhew a man the way to heaven? Surely it can not: becauſe it ſits beſide the divine Revelation, which is the onely record wherein the way to life is referved for vs. I ſay heaven and eternall happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, is only to be found in Gods Revelation, and who will not beleiue me? for where the end is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue nature, the meanes thereto muſt needes be ſo alſo. What need I then to trouble my ſelfe and the Reader with more arguments? But ſeeing it will not ſaue our labour (ſome are ſo contentious, and will not reſt in truthes apparent) therefore ſuch muſt be met withall, and their endeavours preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: as the frugall man weedes his feild, that his grayne may be the better vnto ſight, and ſervice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 9. <hi>Our Opponent B. his firſt Argument.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WEe are now come to the ſecond part of this Diſcourſe,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> wherein the Arguments for the contrary party are propounded and refuted: and I will begin with our Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent <hi>B.</hi> who brings his firſt Argument, pag. 31. to this effect.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>The ſeat of Antichaiſt is the true Church, for hee ſitts in Gods Temple. <hi>2 Theſſ: 2.4.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:18310:39"/>
                  <item>But the preſent Romiſh Church, is the ſeate of Antichriſt:</item>
                  <item>Therefore the preſent <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church is the true Church.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The Propoſition of this Argument, is ſet forth pag 36. The concluſion is implyed in the title of Chap: 8, pag 31 The aſſumption is wanting.</p>
               <p>I anſwere: he is confident, that,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> no man can deny the Propoſition, pag. 38. but ſayes nothing of the Aſſumption: and no maruaile, for that beggs the queſtion, by preſuming that the Pope is Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt: a point (to many) more doubtfull then the preſent concluſion. But that fault though it ſpoiles all, (for this time) ſhall goe for nothing.</p>
               <p>The Propoſition is not onely falſe,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> but it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to be true: for the ſeat of Antichriſt is a certaine ſpace, or place, that receiveth the perſon of Antichriſt: and where he governes. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 16.19.17.9.18.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. The true Church is a ſociety of men profeſſing the revealed truth. If then this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion be that place, or neceſſarily flowes from the internall being thereof, (which is impoſſible) then his Propoſition may be true.</p>
               <p>The Aſſumption hath the ſame fault,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church is a ſociety profeſſing their religion: now, it is not poſſible for the perſon of Antichriſt to be contained in the profeſſion of religion, as in a ſpace or place.</p>
               <p>To conclude,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> if we put this Syllogiſme into its true and naturall termes, theſe will be the words thereof.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>The ſpace containing the perſon of Antichriſt, is
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:18310:40"/>that ſociety of men which profeſſeth the revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led verities.</item>
                  <item>But that ſociety which profeſſeth the Romiſh religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is the ſpace containing Antichriſt.</item>
                  <item>Therefore that ſociety which profeſs;eth the Romiſh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, is that ſociety which profeſſeth the revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led verities.</item>
               </list>
               <p>But every child that knowes chalke from cheeſe will laugh at this: therefore it ſhall paſſe as ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous.</p>
               <p>He does imagine,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> that, we will ſay in anſwere to this Argument, that,
<q>Antichriſtianity cannot argue the Church to be Chriſtian, being the bane and plaine overthrow of Chriſtianity. Pag. <hi>36.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer, we doe not thus anſwer to this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, neither need we, vnleſſe our anſwer ſhould be as fond as his proofe, and experience will now iuſtifie the ſame: we haue anſwered otherwayes, and yet his reaſon is refelled,</p>
               <p>Keep your kindneſſe for your friend, and anſwer for vs when wee need it, wee know <hi>Sophocles</hi> ſaid true:</p>
               <q>The guift of an enemy is no guift.</q>
               <p>In the reſt of this 8.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> chapter he hunts the wild gooſe chaſe: but all his long diſcourſe, and many words amounteth in the totall vnto thus much.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>The Iewes Church in their worſt eſtate was the true Church of God. Some of Gods people are in <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore many heretofore, and ſome at this day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing outwardly of the Church of Rome, wee may
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:18310:40"/>iuſtly, notwithſtanding, challenge to our ſelves.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Opponent</hi> C. <hi>ſhall anſwer him, pag. 3.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Prooue and apply Iohn Barber, and thou ſhalt haue two new paire of Sizors.</p>
               </q>
               <p>A recompence too great for ſuch a workeman, yet let me tell you, the Iewes Church at no time, was equall, or ſtood in the ſame termes or conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the preſent Romiſh Church: for they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes retained the true, and vndoubted foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of faith, they relied onely vpon Gods authority the revealer of ſacred things, ſo as what ever they believed, they ſo believed, becauſe God revealed it, they thruſt not in the authority of man between the ſacred revelation, and their faith and credence: ſo as, ſtill they enioyed at leaſt the meanes for get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of divine faith, and conſequently ſalvation it ſelfe; but ſo it is not with the Romiſh Church, as manifeſtly appeareth in former paſſages, cap. 4. num. 7. &amp;c. whereupon we may conclude: Though the Iewiſh Church was the true Church of God: yet that will not inferre the Romiſh Church to be ſo alſo. Moreover, the Iewes defection was in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of practiſe rather then of precept: when they failed in doctrine, it was peculiar to ſome, not vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall and common to all that Church: their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour was matter of opinion, not of faith: for no publick authority of theirs did command that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, or miſbeliefe, to bee vniverſally recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved as being divinely revealed. But with the Church of Rome the matter is altogether other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, Their errour is firſt in precept, and then in practiſe: this errour is common to all in that
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:18310:41"/>Church, no man can be exempted therefrom, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he will profeſſe himſelfe to be none of theirs. Againe, that errour of the Romiſh Church is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudged to be revealed by God, and commaunded to be received by all the members of that Church, by an authority that pretendeth freedome from erring, and power of enioying: ſo as, whatſoever is ſo commanded muſt be obeyed without delay, or inquiring, as is ſhewed, cap. 4. num. 7. &amp;c. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we need not doubt to ſay, the one loſt not the truth of a Church, the other hath not the truth of a Church.</p>
               <p>We may allow God a ſhare in ſome that dwell in <hi>Babylon:</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> but what is that ſhare? Even perſons elected, but not yet called, and vnto ſuch God commandeth that they <hi>Come out of Babylon,</hi> and they ſhall heare and obey in their appointed time. But what is this to vs? Elected perſons, (not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) are ſuch members of the Church as are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne to vs, and therefore are reckoned to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine to the Church inviſible: but out queſtion is of the Church viſible.</p>
               <p>More then ſo, God may require vs to <hi>come out of Babylon,</hi> even vs that are not there, for ſuch a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund is no more but to prevent our going thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: foraſmuch as the ſame perſon that is furtheſt from <hi>Babylon</hi> in this preſent eſtate, is there, (even there already) in poſſibility: becauſe, the holieſt man that liveth, <hi>liveth in the fleſh,</hi> or humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and therfore may he be carried to <hi>Babylon,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Babylon</hi> is hereſie, or at leaſt includes it; and herefie is a fruit of the fleſh. By this time (I hope)
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:18310:41"/>his whole diſcourſe, as well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat is to the purpoſe, as what is beſide the purpoſe, is fully cleered and ſatisfied: wherein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hine departed from the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of an anſwerer, of loue and deſire to ſatisfie the Reader.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 10. <hi>Our Opponent</hi> B. <hi>his ſecond Argument.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HE vrgeth vs, cap. 9. pag. 37.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> with a ſecond Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument concluding after this manner.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>That Society which wanteth the nature of a true Church, denyes fundamentall truth, directly, not by conſequence.</item>
                  <item>But the preſent Romiſh Church, does not deny fundamentall truth directly, but by conſequence (at the moſt:) for the Popes Arithmetick, which he vſeth in calculating the Articles of faith, is not ſubrſtaction, but addition.</item>
                  <item>Therefore the preſent Romiſh Church, wanteth not the nature of a true Church.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The Aſſumption and concluſion, is ſet downe pag 41. and the title of the Chapter, pag 37. The Propoſition is wanting.</p>
               <p>In pag. 21, 22. he writeth thus.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               </p>
               <q>Our adverſaries (in this cauſe) doe bring the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall of the foundation of faith, as a medium to proue the Church of Rome to be no true Church.</q>
               <p>I anſwere, this man hath a faire gift of inventing: ſome while he can finde an adverſary that anſwers,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:18310:42"/>another while one that diſputes, and all is no more but his owne ſhadow, or imagination. If he would haue the Reader to thinke otherwiſe, let him name the Authour that thus diſputes, and the place where we may finde it, till then this muſt goe for falſe.</p>
               <p>None of ours would diſpute ſo, for it preſumes, that, ſome Articles of faith be fundamentall, and ſome be not; and that is falſe: the whole divine revelation conduceth to eternall life, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly it is the foundation thereof, and conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently every Article of faith is fundamentall.</p>
               <p>I anſwere further,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> This reaſon (as it lyeth) doth admit many egregious exceptions, but becauſe I am willing to interpret him with the vttermoſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, I will forbeare to charge him with them.</p>
               <p>He confines <hi>fundamentall trueth vnto the being of the Scriptures, and Chriſts comming to ſaue ſinners: pag.</hi> 19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20. <hi>To deny fundamentall trueth (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to him) directly, is directly to deny that [Ieſus Chriſt came into the world to ſaue ſinners] as Pagans, Turkes, and Iewes doe: pag.</hi> 22. <hi>They deny it by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent, which holding it directly, maintaine any one aſſertion whatſoever whereupon the direct deniall thereof may be neceſſarily concluded. Thus the</hi> Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians <hi>holding Circumciſion, did by conſequence over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw ſalvation by Chriſt, inaſmuch as, it was impoſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that they ſhould ſtand together: pag.</hi> 23, 24.</p>
               <p>According vnto this explication, this Argument will be freeſt from exception if it bee framed in theſe termes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:18310:42"/>
               <head>CHAP. 11. <hi>Of the ſame Argument new framed.</hi>
               </head>
               <list>
                  <item>THat ſociety which wants the nature of a true Church does, in words,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and profeſſedly deny the Scriptures and Chriſts comming to ſaue ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</item>
                  <item>But the preſent Romiſh Church does not in words, and profeſſedly deny the Scriptures, and Christs comming to ſaue ſinners.</item>
                  <item>Therefore the preſent Romiſh Church, wants not the nature of a true Church.</item>
               </list>
               <p>His proofes for this Aſſumption are two, the one, pag. 126. in theſe words:
<q>Offer the fundamentall words to them of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church, and none amongst them will refuſe to ſubſcribe vnto them.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The other is his fifth Argument, pag. 59. &amp;c: To proue the maine queſtion: ſo deſirous he is to make ſhewes of plenty, that one ſhall be divided into two, rather then he will be ſhort in number. In that, he writeth thus:
<q>In our diſputations with them, we doe not proue that Chriſt came to ſaue ſinners, but we bring it in proofe againſt them: pag. <hi>62.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And this ſayes he is
<q>A tacite conſent of all ours, that the Church of Rome does not directly deny the foundation. pag. <hi>61.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>In pag 70. he writeth thus.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               </p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:18310:43"/>I would gladly ſee the teſtimony of, but, one in eſtimation for his learning, amongſt vs that ever affirmed the Church of Rome to deny the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Faith directly. The Church of <hi>England,</hi> hath not paſſed any ſuch ſentence vpon her.</q>
               <p>Some of ours,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> touching this matter, haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten thus:
<q>The Church of Rome denyeth Chriſt Ieſus direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, not by conſequence onely.</q>
               </p>
               <p>At this our Opponent <hi>B.</hi> pag. 122. growes very angry, and <hi>craues pardon for breaking his long pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> and doth challenge him for an <hi>egregious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, in avouching a deniall direct, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence:</hi> and why? Becauſe, <hi>The foundation cannot be overthrowne both by conſequence, and directly too. None can overthrow by conſequence, vnleſſe they hold directly, and no man can both hold directly, and deny directly:</hi> And in concluſion, he does grauely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend that Author, becauſe he labour to proue, that, the Church of Rome is guilty of ſuch deniall, both directly, and by conſequence; ſeeing ſuch proofe makes the whole fall to the ground, being nothing worth: and leaſt ſomething ſhould be wanting pertaining to the honour of a learned Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puter, he giues his word for all this, eſteeming the leaſt proofe his great diſgrace.</p>
               <p>I anſwere,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> If I proue that the Church of Rome directly denies the being of the Scriptures and the comming of Chriſt to ſaue ſinners, I doe enough to ſatisfie this Argument, even by the confeſſion of this Opponent: for, pag. 124. he writes thus: <hi>If you can proue the Church of Rome directly to deny ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:18310:43"/>by Chriſt, alone, we binde our ſelves to grant you the victory, and yours be the day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If I proue the Church of Rome by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, alſo, ſo to deny, then that Authour hath made no contradiction by this Opponents owne rule: namely, becauſe <hi>both of them may be true toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Opponent demandeth <hi>how, or where that proofe ſhall be had, and made,</hi> pag. 124. I anſwere, I will haue that proofe out of the Councel of <hi>Trent,</hi> and frame it according to art, and the rules of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering; for that is my office at this time. Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the firſt.</p>
               <p>I anſwere: to deny and affirme is made by voice,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> and accordingly to deny and affirme may be by the voice of humane reaſon, or divine faith. This I take as granted, elſe there can be no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Heathen Philoſophers, Turks, and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, when they all profeſſe, even in ſo many words, <hi>That there is a God.</hi> In the firſt ſenſe I grant the Aſſumption, (that is) The Romiſh Church profeſſeth, even in ſo many words, the being of the Scriptures, and the comming of Chriſt, by the voice of humane reaſon: and ſo farre we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to goe along with this Opponent: but the Propoſition is falſe. This we ſay, The profeſſion of the Scriptures, and of Chriſts comming to ſaue ſinners, by the voice of humane faith, though it be in words never ſo plaine and expreſſe, yet it giues not being to the Church, for the Church ſubſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in it ſelfe, and differeth from all other ſocieties, by ſupernaturall, not by naturall, or humane en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments:
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:18310:44"/>and this I take as granted.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond ſenſe the Propoſition is true, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, The profeſſion, even in ſo many words, of theſe fundamentall truthes: <hi>[There be Scriptures] [Chriſt came to ſaue ſinners] by the voice of divine faith is the very ſoule of the Church, and ſo eſſentiall therto, that without it there can be no Chriſtian Church, and where that is, the Church is alſo: becauſe it is ſo operatiue whereſoever it doth encline, that all other things requiſite to a Chriſtian Church does follow:</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as this Opponent writeth, pag. 21.29.34.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 12. <hi>The Romiſh Church directly denies ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation by Chriſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BVt in this ſenſe the Aſſumption is falſe,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the preſent Romiſh Church does in words, and profeſſedly deny the being of the Scriptures, and the comming of Chriſt to ſaue ſinners, according vnto the voice of divine faith: and I proue it thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They that doe not confeſſe Chriſts comming to ſaue ſinners, doe profeſſedly deny his comming to ſaue ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: for in this caſe, a not confeſsion, is a profeſſed ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, and ſo accounted by our Saviour, who ſaith, he that is not with me is againſt me; he that gathereth not, ſcattereth: Matth.</hi> 12.30. And good reaſon hee ſhould ſo eſteeme it: for ſuch a not confeſſion, is a voluntary omiſſion of our duty; <hi>This is the will of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:18310:44"/>my heavenly Father, that yee beleeue on him whom hee hath ſent. Ioh.</hi> 6.29. Even all men whatſoever, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>earth is his inheritance, and the vttermoſt ends thereof is his poſſeſsion. Pſal.</hi> 2.8. Wee ſee the truth hereof in the omiſſion of any duty. Hee that withheld his tythes, is held profeſſedly to deny the paying of tythes. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.8. He that honoureth not his parents, is reckoned profeſſedly to diſhonour his Parents. <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.6. This Propoſition then being very evident, I thus aſſume.</p>
               <p>But the Romiſh Church doth not confeſſe Chriſts comming to ſaue ſinners, by the voice of divine faith: becauſe the faith of that Church (by meanes of the foundation thereof) is humane, and not divine, as hath beene manifeſtly proved, cap. 4. num. 7. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>He thinks to ſhrowd himſelfe vnder the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of our Church,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> which hee vrgeth negatiuely thus.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Our Church does charge her to erre in matter of faith, Art. <hi>19</hi> but not with direct deniall of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation by Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Therefore the Romiſh Church is not ſo to bee char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</p>
               </q>
               <p>I anſwer, 1. he takes the authority of our Church to be of moment, I demand then, why he diſputes againſt her all this while, yea againſt her doctrine ſubſcribed by himſelfe? 2. The conſequence is nought, our Churches ſilence argues not the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church to be innocent, for this queſtion of denying or not denying, was not in being when her faith was publiſhed. This was done, Anno
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:18310:45"/>1562. that began, Anno 1588. or neere thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for any thing I can yet learne, or this Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent proue. 3. The Antecedent is falſe; for two reaſons. 1. Errours in matters of faith may be a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect deniall of ſalvation by Chriſt; for he that ſo denies, errs in matter of faith; and we muſt thinke our Church meant ſo: becauſe her words will beare it, and this Opponent cannot ſhew the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. 2. Our Church in the ſecond Homily for <hi>Whitſontide</hi> (often times already alledged) does de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny her <hi>to be built vpon Chriſt the corner ſtone in that foundation,</hi> and that importeth a direct deniall of ſalvation by Chriſt: becauſe he that ſits be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that foundation, ſhall goe without ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>This proofe and defence being conſidered,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> we may ſafely reſt in this concluſion. <hi>The Romiſh Church according to the voice of divine faith, profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly denies Chriſts comming to ſaue ſinners,</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly we haue the victory, and ours is the day: according to this Opponents offer and our accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, num. 4. chap. 11. I might proceed to proue their profeſſed deniall of the Scriptures vpon the ſame ground, but I forbeare to doe it; becauſe the Reader may ſee this Argument ſerues for both that, and this, by changing the termes.</p>
               <p>This Opponent ſeemeth to qualifie his former recited promiſe,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and calleth vs, as he thinkes, to a new reckoning, pag. 22, 23. wherein hee writeth thus:
<q>They overthrow the foundation directly, to whom Chriſt is an execration, And to tread vnder foot
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:18310:45"/>the ſonne of God, to count the blood of the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant wherewith all wee are ſanctified, an vnholy thing, and to doe deſpite vnto the ſpirit of grace. <hi>Heb. 10.29.</hi> is directly to deny the foundation.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And then, he aſſumes in theſe words:
<q>Of which crime, whoſoever is able, let him indict the Church of Rome, producing ſufficient evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence thereof: and whoſoever ſhall open his mouth to plead for them, let him be guilty of all the diſhonour, that ever hath beene done to the Sonne of God, and lyable to the Apoſtles curſe: <hi>1 Cor. 16.22.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwere, this is his laſt refuge:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> if therefore he failes in this, he is gone for ever. In true forme he reaſoneth thus:</p>
               <list>
                  <item>They that directly deny ſalvation by Chriſt, are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as aforeſaid.</item>
                  <item>But the Romiſh Church are not ſo guilty.</item>
                  <item>Therefore the Romiſh Church denies not directly ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation by Chriſt.</item>
               </list>
               <p>I may except againſt the Aſſumption with bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reaſon then he can argue for it: wherefore this I ſay, <hi>The Romiſh Church is ſo guilty</hi> for, They that know and belieue Chriſts comming to ſaue ſinners onely by naturall reaſon, and humane faith, <hi>They tread him vnder foote, account his blood vnholy, and doe deſpite vnto the ſpirit of grace.</hi> Heb. 10.29. <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, the naturall man perceiveth (or receiveth not) the things of God, (as they are the things of God) for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as they are ſpiritually diſcerned.</hi> 1 Cor. 2.14.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The very wiſedome of the fleſh is enmitie vnto God.</hi> Rom. 8.7. But the Romiſh Church does know
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:18310:46"/>and beleiue Chriſts comming to ſaue ſinners; only by naturall reaſon, and humaine faith: for all their knowledge, and beleiving, ariſeth vpon the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Paſtors of their Church, which is meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly humaine, becauſe they haue no Commiſſion for ſuch teaching, as appeareth Cap. 4. num. 7. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>If any man doe iudge that the place alledged, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.29. mean no more but thus, then I reſt here as in a ſufficient anſwer to this argument, and claim this Opponents finall promiſe laſt mentioned, and ſo we are at an end for this cauſe: the day is ours, we muſt carry the victory, and the ſignes thereof, leading theſe Opponents in tryumph.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> If the Apoſtle be vnderſtood to ſpeake of more then this, then I deny the Propoſition, as wanting the very ſhew of truth. I ſay, ſome men directly deny ſalvation by Chriſt, who are not guiltie as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid; and, I haue two reaſons for it, the firſt is this: Iewes and Pagans are not guilty as aforeſaid: for the parties ſo guilty, haue received the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the truth, and <hi>afterwards ſinne wilfully, ver.</hi> 26. <hi>by forſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>king the Aſſembly of the faithfull, verſ.</hi> 25. and therefore are certeinely ſubiected vnto Gods fiery devouring indignation and iudgment, ver. 27. But Iewes and Pagans deny ſalvation by Chriſt, (in the iudgement of this Opponent pag 22.) Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, if all that directly deny ſalvation by Chriſt are thus guiltie, then this guiltines in the Apoſtles intent is the totall, and adaequate nature of that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyall, otherwiſe the Propoſition conteineth not an vniverſall truth. But this guiltines (in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles intent) is not the totall and adaequate nature
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:18310:46"/>of that denyall: but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> denyall in one ſpeciall kinde, viz. Apoſtacy, and wilfull backſliding: for thus lyes the Apoſtles reaſon. If wilfull forſakers of their profeſſion, and the ſociety of the Saints, ſhall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly bee puniſhed with Gods fiery devouring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, and judgement, then let vs hold faſt the profeſſion of our faith, and the aſſembly of the Saints without wavering.</p>
               <p>But ſuch ſhall be ſo puniſhed: for their ſinne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues it, inaſmuch as, thereby they tread vnder foote the Sonne of God, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The Propoſition and Aſſumption is ſet forth from verſe 23. to the end of verſe 27. and the proofe of the Aſſumption verſe 29. (being the place which we haue now in hand) whereupon we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude: Some that directly deny ſalvation by Chriſt, are not thus guilty; and ſo his Propoſition is falſe, that maketh all ſuch deniers to be ſo guilty, and conſequently, our Mother the Church of England hath the day of victory, and ſo ſhall hold it.</p>
               <p>Theſe Opponents are vnder the hatches, and there we will keepe them.</p>
               <p>This Opponent telleth vs, pag. 123.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> that we ſhall not need to proue, that, The Romiſh Church denies ſalvation by Chriſt by conſequence: he will pardon vs that labour, to the end that the Reader ſhould ſee, &amp; we confeſſe him to be a fair adverſary.</p>
               <p>I anſwere, and why does he account this pardon a favour done vs, ſeeing himſelfe does confeſſe the thing it ſelfe, ſo often: does he thinke, himſelfe can doe what we cannot? Surely then, what dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:18310:47"/>he from the <hi>Bold Braggadochiaes</hi> in the Campe, whereof wee reade in his partner Opponents Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle. It may be he will ſay, he that makes that proofe muſt grant, that they directly hold ſalvation by Chriſt, which he does, and we doe not. I reply, he is deceived, we doe ſay, they directly hold ſalvation by Chriſt, according to the voice of humane faith, as I haue anſwered, chap. 11. num. 5. therefore if any thing makes the difference between his power to proue, and ours, It is not his affirmation, and our negation; but he hath skill and we haue none, well, let him vaunt that hath the vayne, To the preſent matter, we ſay, we deſpiſe his pardon, we craue no favour, let him doe his worſt, wee know whoſe faith we maintaine, and will now proue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 13. <hi>The Romiſh Church by conſequence de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies ſalvation by Chriſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN proofe of this ſentence,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> I will content my ſelfe with an Argument in this forme.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>They that directly hold ſalvation by Chriſt, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things which cannot ſtand therewith, they by conſequence deny ſalvation by Chriſt: becauſe from the ſecond, the direct dentall of the firſt may be neceſſarily concluded.</item>
                  <item>But the Romiſh Church directly holds ſalvation by Chriſt, and other things that cannot ſtand there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</item>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:18310:47"/>
                  <item>Therefore the Romiſh Church by conſequence denies ſalvation by Chriſt.</item>
               </list>
               <p>This Opponent may not deny any part of this Argument: becauſe the Propoſition &amp; the proofe thereof is his owne, pag 23. &amp; 24. ſo is the Aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, pag. 26. The concluſion is gathered out of them both, who therefore (on this mans behalfe) can except againſt any part thereof.</p>
               <p>It may be ſome man may ſay,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> In all the former paſſages we haue charged the <hi>Romiſh Church,</hi> with a direct deniall of ſalvation by Chriſt, and in this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument we free that Church, from ſuch denyall, and conſequently we contradict our ſelues, ſo as the proofe of the one, doth equally overthrow the proofe of the other, and thus our opponent ſeemes to argue, as I haue reported, Cap. 11. num. 3. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, this exception may be taken off with eaſe: for we charge them and diſcharge them as is aforeſaid, indifferent reſpects, we ſay they deny ſalvation by Chriſt according vnto, or in reſpect of divine faith, we grant them the contradictory according vnto, or in reſpect of naturall reaſon or humaine faith, as the Reader may finde, cap. 11. num. 5. In regard whereof, both ſentences and their proofes may e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually ſtand together, without domage the one to the other. If any man thinkes otherwiſe, he muſt ſhew it by the rules of Art, elſe no man is bound to beleiue him. I anſwer further, this direct hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſalvation by Chriſt, which wee grant vnto them, is inducement &amp; foundation enough, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon we may charge them with the denyall of the ſame thing by conſequence? For that holding is a
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:18310:48"/>reall confeſſion, and accordingly doth put the thing confeſſed in a being ſufficient, whereupon it may be denyed, or avoyded by inference, and therefore our Propoſition is true, that ſuppoſeth the ſame.</p>
               <p>And thus our Argument is ſufficiently fenced, againſt the clawes of this Opponent: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore here I muſt end the matter of their denyall of ſalvation by Chriſt by conſequence: for none of our Opponents brings more then thus touching the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Some man perhaps would accompt it a thing worth our labour, if we reſted not in theſe Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponents confeſſion for the truth of our Aſſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but avowed the ſame thing by the Records of the Romiſh faith. To whom I anſwer: that deſire is not vnmeet, nor the thing hard to to be done, but the preſent buſineſſe, and my office muſt not be forgotten. If I entred vpon that, wee ruſh into another queſtion. I am now to anſwere, but hee that does that, muſt proue. This Aſſumption is confeſſed by all parties, therefore it is a principle, and accordingly it may make an Argument in this queſtion, &amp; therfore it muſt paſſe as a thing certain.</p>
               <p>Accordingly here we would reſt, but our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Opponent is not ſo contented: for hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes, that, the <hi>Romiſh Church</hi> may be <hi>ranked with the old Hereticks, becauſe they goe not the ſame way to worke with them;</hi> They (ſaith he) <hi>ſtruck neerer the head then the Church of Rome does. She indeed is wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred from God, and her doctrine is iniurous and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumelious to God and our Redeemer: It doth gainſay
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:18310:48"/>the foundation of our faith: but yet it is remooued a great diſtance therefrom: raze it, it doth: but by a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of conſequence (at the moſt)</hi> thus he writes pag 3. 18. 24. 25. 38. 41. 127. 128. <hi>Yet he does not varniſh o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their opinion, nor help the beſt foote of a lame cauſe forward;</hi> if you will beleiue his words pag 127. For this cauſe therefore, I will prooue the Romiſh Church to deny ſalvation by Chriſt, by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, direct and immediate, not by a circle, or meanes that comes betweene that proofe and that ſalvation: and then wee ſhall know, whether that Church ranks with the old hereticks or not, and whether this Opponent is not a faithfull advocate vnto her or not. I frame my proofe thus.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> If ſome Articles of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> faith in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues be oppoſite to this ſentence. [Saluation is by Chriſt] then that Church denyes ſaluation by Chriſt, by a conſequence that is direct &amp; immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, not by circle and the interpoſing of others: for ſuch is the nature of oppoſites, that both of them cannot befall the ſame ſubiect, in the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, part and time, by reaſon whereof, the affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation or preſence of the one, is a denyall &amp; ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the other, as <hi>Aliaco</hi> doeth truely teach. <hi>1. ſent. q. 2. lit: H.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>But ſome Articles of the Romiſh faith, in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, be oppoſite to this ſentence [Saluation is by Christ.]</item>
                  <item>Therefore the Romiſh Church, denyes Salvation by Chriſt, by a conſequence that is direct &amp; immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, not circular by the interpoſing of others.</item>
               </list>
               <p>In the avowry of my Aſſumption, I will proue three things.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:18310:49"/>1. According to the Romiſh Church.</p>
               <q>Inherent grace, merits and ſatisfaction of mans worke, is the next and formall reaſon of our ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle vnto, and the poſſeſsion of heaven.</q>
               <p n="2">2. According to the Scriptures.</p>
               <q>Ieſus Christ is the next and formall reaſon of our title vnto, and the poſſeſsion of heaven.</q>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Theſe two Articles are oppoſite in themſelues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When I haue manifeſted theſe three, our Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſtandeth firme of all foure, (as we ſay) It is ſound in all parts, and crazed in nothing.</p>
               <p>Touching the firſt; The Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> hath decreed thus:
<q>
                     <p>Chriſt is the Authour of our ſalvation. <hi>Seſſ. 6. Cap. 11.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>By Chriſt we haue grace. <hi>Can. 2.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>He merits grace for vs. <hi>Cap. 7. &amp; 16.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>From him grace flowes vnto vs, as the ſap into the branches. <hi>Cap. 16.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In him, (that is he working with vs) we merit, and ſatisfie. <hi>Seſſ. 14. Cap. 8. de ſatisfact.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>His grace makes our woorkes meritorious. <hi>Seſſ. 6. Cap. 16.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Gods will makes them our merits. <hi>Cap. 16. Can. 32.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Thus farr Chriſt hath ſhare (according to them) in our ſalvation, we will ſee now what place they aſſigne vnto inherent grace, with the merit and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of our workes.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Eternall life is propounded as the grace of ſons, and wages vnto workes. <hi>Seſſ. 6. Cap. 16.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By grace received wee are made iuſt of vniuſt,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:18310:49"/>that we might be heires of eternall life according to hope. <hi>Cap. 7.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Inherent grace is a fountaine in him that hath it, ſpringing vnto eternall life. <hi>Cap. 16.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The iuſt doe carry their grace before Gods Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and enioy heaven. <hi>Cap. 7.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The workes of the iuſtified, wrought in God, doe truely inherit the obtaining of eternall life in due time, if they continue therein vnto the end. <hi>Cap. 16.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The iuſt ought to expect and hope for eternall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution from God for their works done in God, if they continue in his law to the end. <hi>Can. 26.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The iuſtified by their workes done in grace, doe truly merit eternall life, the increaſe of grace, glory, and eternall life it ſelfe: if they die in grace. <hi>Can. 32.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>Now (I preſume) I haue made it very manifeſt, that they attribute vnto Chriſt no other part in our ſalvation, but the office of giving vs grace, and therefore we are beholden to him for no more, but the beginning and the poſſibility of ſalvation; but vnto inherent grace, and the merit of worke, they aſſigne the next and formall reaſon of our ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in hope while we liue here, and in poſſeſſion when we are gone from hence.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> In this place we muſt inquire what office is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to the ſatisfaction of good workes, and for that we reade theſe Decrees in the Councell.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>By the grace of Iuſtification received, the fault is remitted, and the guiltineſſe of eternall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment is blotted out: yet ſometimes remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:18310:50"/>a guiltineſſe of temporall puniſhment, to be ſatisfied for, either in this world, or in Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in the world to come, before the way to Gods Kingdome can be opened. <hi>Seſſ. 6. Can. 30.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wee are able to ſatisfie before God, not onely by thoſe puniſhments, which we willingly vnder goe for the revenge of ſinne, or impoſed by the prieſt according to the meaſure of our fault: but alſo, even by ſuch temporall afflictions, which God layeth vpon vs, and we beare with patience. <hi>Seſſ. 14. cap. 9. de operibus, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wee are able to ſatisfie God, and doe ſo, for our ſinnes. By Ieſus Chriſt, he working together with vs, wee are able to doe all things: from whom our good workes receiue force, of whom they are offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Father, and by whom they are accepted of the Father. <hi>Seſſ: 14. cap. 8. de ſatisfact. cap. 9. de operibus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>As in the former, ſo here, they make the ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of our works, <hi>the key to open heaven gates,</hi> and the reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence for iniury done to God, but Chriſt, he ſhall haue no more part in the buſineſſe, but to make vs able to <hi>turne the key,</hi> if he help vs we neede no more of him, we do the reſt our ſelues.</p>
               <p>Wee no ſooner <hi>turne the Key,</hi> but in we goe: If we make recompence we are diſcharged, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, the ſatisfaction of our owne workes, is the next and formall reaſon of our releaſe from Purgatorie, and the opening of heaven gates.</p>
               <p>I haue done enough in proofe of the firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> and now come to the ſecond. For that I haue leſſe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, becauſe the Scriptures are full and plaine for it: as followeth.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:18310:50"/>
                  <p>If the Sonne make you free, you ſhall be free in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. <hi>Ioh: 8.36.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hee that beletueth in the Sonne, is paſſed from death vnto life. <hi>Ioh: 5.24. and 3.26.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wee ſhall be ſaued by his life. <hi>Rom. 5.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We are ioynt heyres with him. <hi>Rom: 8.17.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hee brings many children to glory. <hi>Heb. 2.10.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt. <hi>Rom. 8.1.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Chriſt was once offred to beare the ſins of many, and he ſhall appeare the ſecond time without ſinne vnto ſaluation. <hi>Heb 9.28.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Chriſts takes away the ſins of the world. <hi>Io. 1.29.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Chriſt once in the end of the world appeared to put away ſinne, by the Sacrifice of himſelfe. <hi>Heb. 9.26.</hi> and is entred into heauen it ſelfe, to appear in the preſence of God for vs. <hi>ibidem v. 24.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>If any man doubt whether theſe places do make Chriſt the next &amp; formall reaſon of our ſaluation, he may ſatisfie himſelfe by the phraſe, which the holy Ghoſt vſeth: for hee makes an imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate connexion betweene Chriſt and heaven, which he would not doe ſo often, if ſome thing elſe came betweene Chriſt and heaven: for to ſet forth a remote and mediate cauſe, by a next &amp; immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, is an improper, and borrowed ſpeech, which is an vndecent thing to be ſo often (and more often then thus) in the pen of the holy Ghoſt: If then we dare not charge him ſo, we muſt conceiue hee meant to make Chriſt the next and formall reaſon of our ſaluation.</p>
               <p>I need not proue Chriſt and mans merits to be
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:18310:51"/>oppoſite next and formall reaſons of our ſalvation, for it is manifeſt by it ſelfe: ſo as, now our Aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion num. 4. is ſufficiently confirmed, let the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der iudge of our cauſe, and the preſent Opponent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 14. <hi>They that deny ſalvation by Chriſt by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence are not the true Church.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Argument propounded,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Chap. 11. num. 1. preſumes the contradictory to this poſition, and this our preſent Opponent, pag. 25. and 26. does expreſſely teach it, in theſe words:
<q>Whole Churches haue denied, (and yet doe) deny by conſequence, that ſalvaton is by Chriſt: yet we doe, and muſt hold them Chriſtian.</q>
               </p>
               <p>All this while we haue let that ſuppoſition paſſe vntouched, as if it were true: becauſe the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of that proofe ſhould be the more apparent: but now (and in all good time) we ſay, he ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth falſely, and therefore he is a begger, no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
               <p>We proue againſt him with this Argument.</p>
               <q>Vnto the true Church Chriſt may bee profitable, Vnto ſuch as deny by conſequence that ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is by Chriſt, Chriſt cannot be profitable: for vnto the <hi>Gallatians</hi> Chriſt could not be profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. <hi>Gallat. 5.2, 3, 4.</hi> But all ſuch as deny by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, that ſalvation is by Chriſt, are the <hi>Gallatians. 5.2, 3, 4. I ſay they are the ſame
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:18310:51"/>with them, not by name, Nation, ſingular perſons, or doctrine: but in their deniall they are the ſame, (that is) the one denies ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by Chriſt by illation inference and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, and ſo doe all other. The</hi> Gallatians <hi>held ſomething for true:</hi> viz. [Salvation is by the Law] <hi>This being granted, then muſt we deny that</hi> Salvation is by Chriſt. <hi>So ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it with all others that by conſequence deny him to bring ſalvation. Whereupon we may conclude: All ſuch as by conſequence denie ſalvation by Chriſt, Chriſt can profit them nothing, and conſequently,</hi> ſuch as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny by conſequence that ſalvation is by Christ, are not the true Church.</q>
               <p>I conceiue, in pag. 24.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> he meant (at leaſt he might with the matter there contained) diſpute with this Argument.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>The <hi>Gallatians</hi> by conſequence denied ſalvation by Chriſt. <hi>Gallat. 5.2. &amp;c.</hi> The <hi>Gallatians, Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat. 5.2. &amp;c.</hi> were a true Church.</p>
                  <p>Therefore ſome true Church, by conſequence denies ſalvation by Chriſt.</p>
               </q>
               <p>I anſwere, thoſe <hi>Gallatians</hi> whereof we reade, <hi>Gallat.</hi> 5.2, 3, 4. by conſequence denied ſalvation by Chriſt, &amp; therefore the Propoſition is true: but that the Apoſtle writes there, of the whole Church of <hi>Gallatia,</hi> may not reaſonably be affirmed, nor can poſſibly be proved; becauſe, no part of Gods word doth ſay ſo, or leade vs to thinke ſo. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle in the 5. Chapter, reproues the <hi>Gallatians,</hi> for <hi>biting, and devouring one another,</hi> verſe 15. and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:18310:52"/>for <hi>vaine glory, and envie,</hi> verſe 26. Now the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties thus reproved were particular perſons, not ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally the whole Church: for, it is not likely, that every ſingular man in <hi>Gallatia</hi> was ſo guilty: if ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſingular perſons were reproved here, then there alſo: for the ſame phraſe and manner of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe, is vſed both there and here.</p>
               <p>If any man be deſirous,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> to haue vs vnderſtand the Apoſtle of the whole Church of <hi>Gallatia,</hi> verſ. 2, 3, 4. we may doe it without profit to this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>For then, I grant, them of <hi>Gallatia</hi> were a true Church: becauſe the Apoſtle, cap. 1. verſe 2. terms them a <hi>Church,</hi> and ſaluteth them <hi>with grace and peace from God and Chriſt,</hi> verſe 3. and does ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge them to haue received <hi>libertie,</hi> and <hi>freeaome by Chriſt,</hi> cap. 5. verſe 1. We may conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, that, they ioyned <hi>Circumciſion, and the keeping of Moſes Law, vnto Chriſt,</hi> in opinion, not as mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of faith. At that time they began to grow in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king with that conceit; but they were not confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and ſetled in their iudgement that God had revealed it, nor profeſſed it to the world as ſuch. If they did ſo indeed, then I may grant the whole reaſon without loſſe; becauſe, the concluſion vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth not vs: we willingly acknowledge, that the true Church is ſubiect to errour, in opinion, in things very important vnto ſalvation: we onely deny that erring in matter of faith can befall the true Church, whileſt it is ſo. I ſay we may thus iudge of that Church, vntill we ſee good reaſon for the contrary: becauſe, <hi>charity thinketh not evill,</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:18310:52"/>nor is ſuſpitious. Nay, the Apoſtles phraſe lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs to thinke ſo: for, if that had beene a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of faith with them, hee would haue charged them with the fact as a thing perfectly done: but he does not ſo, yea rather the contrary: for, verſe 1. he wills them <hi>to ſtand faſt in their Chriſtian libertie:</hi> and, verſe 2. he puts the matter to an <hi>If,</hi> ſaying, <hi>If yee be circumciſed,</hi> &amp;c: verſe 7. he tells them, <hi>yee did runne well, and demands who it was that did let them,</hi> &amp;c. and verſe 10. and 12. he threatneth, and intreateth for their puniſhment that did <hi>trouble them:</hi> and finally, verſe 10. he ſhewes himſelfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, that they would ſhake off, and forſake the preſent doctrine, and <hi>continue in the ſame minde,</hi> vnto which he had brought them, and in which he had left them: wherein it is very apparent, he ſpeakes of them as men wavering, not as parties confirmed in their iudgement.</p>
               <p>Theſe things conſidered, we may vndoubtedly reſolue, that, the Church of <hi>Gallatia,</hi> is no exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, wherein we finde that deniall of ſalvation by Chriſt by conſequence, which is the thing we ſeeke for, and deny to the Church. And thus much ſhall ſuffice in refutation of his great, and important ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, propounded, cap. num.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 15. <hi>Of the ſame Opponents third Argument.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HItherto we haue diſcuſſed,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> all that he hath to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:18310:53"/>ſay, touching the Romiſh Churches acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and publike profeſſion of the Scriptures, and of ſalvation by Chriſt, and haue inſiſted therein to the vttermoſt, leſt ſome ſhould be deceiued by thoſe glorious and beautifull titles. In this place we muſt examine, what good their Baptiſme does them, wherein we may ſay thus much (aforehand) If their profeſſion of the Scriptures, and ſalvation by Chriſt, does not grace them: but notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſuch profeſſion, they remaine ſtill deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of the nature of Chriſts Church, then doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Baptiſme cannot helpe them to it, even in this Opponents iudgement; for pag. 85. he delivers it for a ruled caſe, that, <hi>The Church of God may want Baptiſme for a time, and yet remaine a true Church:</hi> But he will not ſay ſo of profeſſing the Scriptures and ſalvation by Chriſt; which we belieue, and he affirmes, is the ſoule of the Church.</p>
               <p>From their Baptiſme hee frameth this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>That ſociety which conſiſteth of perſons Baptized, that is the true Church.</item>
                  <item>But the Romiſh Church conſiſteth of perſons Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed.</item>
                  <item>Therefore the Romiſh Church, is a true Church.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The Aſſumption, and concluſion, is plainly (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough) ſet forth in the title of chap. 10. pag. 42. and in pag. 45. The Propoſition is wanting, but all the reſt of the Chapter containes no more, but a proofe thereof.</p>
               <p>I anſwere:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                  <hi>The Sacraments duely adminiſtred ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Chriſts ordinance, in all thoſe things that of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:18310:53"/>neceſsity are requiſite to the ſame,</hi> is of the internall, and formall being of the Church, I willingly grant with our Church of <hi>England,</hi> which giues the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments (in this ſenſe) a place in the definition of a Church, Artic. 19. and accordingly, in this ſenſe, I grant the Propoſition, and ſay, that, <hi>That ſociety wherein Baptiſme is thus adminiſtred, and conſiſteth of parties thus Baptized, that is a true Church:</hi> and he may ſaue his labour to proue it, becauſe all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians will confeſſe, that <hi>ſuch Sacraments are peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars to the Church; Teſtimonies of Gods gracious dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and favour, Pledges of his inviſible grace, ſeales of the agreement betweene him, and his Church, and badges to diſtinguiſh the ſame from all others: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, no ſociety elſe, does carry the like vnto them, in the things themſelves, and the loue of the Church:</hi> as this Opponent ſetteth forth, pag, 33.</p>
               <p>But I deny the Aſſumption, and ſay, <hi>The Romiſh Baptiſme is the ſhell and relique of Baptiſme:</hi> and I will now make it appeare, though this Opponent of ours ſeemes to be tragically mooved, and in a pelting fume thereat; inſomuch that hee confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth himſelfe to make good vſe of a <hi>bridle,</hi> pag. 46. and 47. and it is well, ſo good an inſtrument was preſent; for the further he had roved, the more he had miſſed of the true marke.</p>
               <p>The Romiſh Baptiſme is the <hi>ſhell,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and relique of Baptiſme,</hi> no Baptiſme duly adminiſtred, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, I proue it by the authoritie of our Church, in the ſecond Homilie for Whitſontide (often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times already quoted) which expreſſely ſaith, <hi>the Church of Rome does not order the Sacraments</hi> (and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:18310:54"/>therefore this of Baptiſme) <hi>in ſuch ſort as Chriſt did firſt inſtitute, and ordaine them: but, haue ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termingled their owne traditions, and inventions by chopping, and changing, by adding, and plucking away, that now, they may ſeeme to bee converted into a new guiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Will our preſent Opponent thinke this inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, to proue the Romiſh Baptiſme a <hi>ſhell and relique of Baptiſme?</hi> I hope not: if he does oppoſe it as not ſufficient, his partners words, pag. 17. ſhall ſerue him, <hi>O mouth! ô forehead!</hi> and he well deſerues it: what? One man inſtruct a whole Church, yea his Mother that bred him, whoſe Articles of faith gaue him his firſt life, and confirmed him in it, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince? Nay will he afront himſelfe, (yea him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe) not in tranſient words, but in manent letters, his ſubſcription made with his owne hand, for he hath ſubſcribed this Homily.</p>
               <p>Perhaps he will ſay,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> his latter thoughts are bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then his firſt, and to returne to the better, is more decent, then to remaine in the worſer: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I will confirm the ſame thing by other proofe: which I frame thus: The Articles, &amp; doctrine of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine faith, of neceſſitie are requiſite to Baptiſme, I ſay requiſite, previally, &amp; by anteceſſion, not really, and vnto conſtitution: ſuch doctrine muſt precede the Sacrament, though formally it makes not the Sacrament. I proue it: <hi>Gods covenant, and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with man,</hi> of neceſſity muſt precede Baptiſme, for (according to this Opponent) <hi>Baptiſme is the ſeale thereof.</hi> But the Articles of divine faith, are Gods covenant, and agreement with man. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:18310:54"/>the Articles of divine ſaith, of neceſſitie muſt precede Baptiſme. If they muſt ſo precede, then the Romiſh Baptiſme is not adminiſtred accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Chriſts ordinance, in all things of neceſſity requiſite vnto the ſame; for the Articles of their faith, are the Popes, and humane; not Gods, and divine; as I haue proved already. If their Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme be not ſo adminiſtred, then it is erronious, and none of Chriſts ordination. If that be ſo, it is a ſhell, and relique of Baptiſme, retaining the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ceremony, and materiall forme; but wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the inward life, and true intention.</p>
               <p>I anſwere further,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> That ſociety which conſiſteth of perſons Baptiſed, according to mans invention, that is not the true Church: for, Chriſts Church, and all the members thereof, are ſheep of his fold, and heare his voice; ſervants of his houſhold, and obey his will. In this ſenſe the Propoſition is falſe; but the Aſſumption is true: wee willingly grant, that, the Romiſh Church conſiſteth of parties Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed according vnto mans deviſing: but this gains them nothing, the Propoſition being falſe, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion is ſo too.</p>
               <p>By way of reply to this anſwere, he averreth, pag. 45. and 46, that,
<q>Popiſh Baptiſme is true Baptiſme, holy, good, and the ordinance of God.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But I know not what law will tye mee to ioyne thereunto; becauſe, himſelfe is vncertaine, and reſteth not in it, one while hee ſaith, he will not trouble himſelfe to proue it till he knowes who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies it: another while, he takes it to be out of all
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:18310:55"/>queſtion, and ſo doth contradict himſelfe: for, if at another time hee will proue it, then it needes proofe, and conſequently it is not without all que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. If it be without all queſtion, then it needes no proofe, for, according to <hi>Ariſtotle, Nothing muſt be proved, but things that may be doubted of</hi> Top. lib. 1. cap. 11. <hi>and he eſteemes him mad, who puts that for a queſtion, that all men grants.</hi> Top. lib. 1. cap. 10.</p>
               <p>In both the pages laſt mentioned, hee diſputes thus:</p>
               <list>
                  <item>He that calls the Sacrament of Baptiſme a ſhell, and relique of Baptiſme, was not guided by Gods Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, diſgraceth Chriſt, and the Sacrament.</item>
                  <item>But our adverſaries in this cauſe, ſo call the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent of Baptiſme: <hi>pag. 35.47.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Therefore our adverſaries in this cauſe, were not guided by Gods Spirit, and diſgrace Chriſt, and the Sacrament.</item>
               </list>
               <p>I anſwere,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> in the proſecution of the laſt Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, we promiſed him two paire of new Sizors: vpon a faire condition we will now increaſe his wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, ſo as, if he can proue, and apply, this preſent Argument, that it may ſerue in any part of this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, he ſhall haue three paire: ſo deſirous are we to make vſe of ſtuffe ſo precious: Let him doe his labour, and his wages are ready. It may be he will ſay, he amplifies the concluſion, and it may be ſo too: but, is he ſo good an Oratour, that, he am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifies before he proues, I hope he forgets not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and his owne rule. Will he one while af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, another while ceny the ſame thing? Now anſwere, then argue, by and by declaime? Surely,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:18310:55"/>this is altogether without his owne appointed or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pag 77. it is meet the Reader ſhould be put in minde of theſe things, leaſt he miſtake the matter, and the learning of the diſputer.</p>
               <p>His mind cannot be at quiet,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> the Popiſh Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me is ſo great a more in his eye, and therefore, pag. 87. hee falls into it againe, and avoucheth thus much:</p>
               <q>
                  <p>The indecent rites, and erronious opinions of the Romiſh Church, cannot make nullities, and eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuate the force of the Sacraments.</p>
                  <p>Their Baptiſme (for the ſubſtance of it) is holy, and good, and effectuall (no doubt) to them that recetue it, as ours.</p>
               </q>
               <p>I anſwere,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> the ſecond branch is a meere repetiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his former anſwere, and impoſeth a conceit vpon vs, viz. that, <hi>The Popiſh erronious opinions, and indecent rites, make void the being and efficacy of the Sacraments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the firſt branch I will ſay nothing, becauſe I haue done enough for that already. In the ſecond he is miſtaken, or a falſe accuſer: if hee will excuſe himſelfe, let him ſhew the Authour, and place of that opinion. This we ſay, and haue ſaid it alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, <hi>They haue no Sacraments, becauſe they haue no divine faith.</hi> And we thinke this conſequence is good: becauſe, the Sacraments haue no being, nor vſe, but in order vnto, and in preſuppoſall of, the divine faith: and I ſuppoſe, our ſtricteſt Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent will ſay no leſſe; for if the Sacraments might be inioyed, in their true and reall being, and naturall efficacy, where divine faith is wanting,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:18310:56"/>then Turks, and Heathen men might haue them, which I know this Opponent (at leaſt) will deny: becauſe, <hi>The Sacraments are peculiars to the Church, making men Chriſtians, and Chriſtianity makes the Church:</hi> for thus he writeth, pag. 117. and 119.</p>
               <p>Hee promiſed to forbeare his proofes till hee found his poſition denied,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> but <hi>the heate within him,</hi> whereof we reade in his Engliſh Epiſtle, would not giue way to that: wherefore, pag. 118. he alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth two, and I will report them in true forme, that the Reader may ſee their ſoundneſſe. In the firſt he concludes thus.</p>
               <q>If they Baptiſe with water in the name of the Father, the Sonne, and the Holy Ghoſt, then their Baptiſme is good, for here is water, and the words of Chriſts Inſtitution, the one the matter, and the other the forme; and both eſſentiall to Baptiſme.</q>
               <p>I anſwere,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> I deny the conſequence, as naught in it ſelfe, and as ill proved: the reaſon of my deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all is given already, ſo as, I might be ſilent here, but repetition will bee vſefull: often practiſe makes things, and men more expert, and facile.</p>
               <p>This proofe ſuppoſeth, that, <hi>Nothing is eſſentiall to Baptiſme,</hi> (that is nothing by Chriſts inſtitution is of neceſſity requiſite vnto the Sacrament of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme) but <hi>water, and the words of Inſtitution.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwere:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> In the Sacrament of Baptiſme admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred according to Chriſts ordinance, wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue a being; or <hi>entitie,</hi> comprehended vnder cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine limits, as all vnite, and individuall things are; taking that Sacrament as an individuall being,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:18310:56"/>made by motion, there is nothing required to the being thereof, but <hi>the water, and words of inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> and ſo farre this Argument ſuppoſeth right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but nothing againſt vs; for we doe not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny an entitie, or being vnto Popiſh Baptiſme: we know, when water is powred on, and the words pronounced, there is a motion, and a thing made by motion, which was not before, and is diſtinct from all other motions, or things made by motion. In the Sacrament (ſo truly adminiſtred) there is likewiſe, beſides the ſaid individuall entity, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; a certaine connotation, or eſſentiall relation, and that three wayes. 1. Of man to God. 2. Of the Sacrament it ſelfe. 3. Of God vnto man. In the firſt relation man ſhewes his obedience to God. In the ſecond and third man is ordered vnto heaven, ſo farre as the Sacrament can: man being thereby <hi>confirmed in the expectation of Gods loue, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of inherent grace.</hi> Now, vnto this relation, or ordering to heaven, more things are eſſentiall then water, and the words of inſtitution: namely the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred revelation, believed by a divine faith: which (I ſay) doth ſo order vs to heaven, by comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their vſe, and promiſing Gods favour, and working grace, to ſuch as vſe them rightly: from the firſt ariſeth our obedience, from the ſecond our aſſured expectation of his favour, and grace: and thus much this Opponent himſelfe will confeſſe I doubt not.</p>
               <p>Nothing (I preſume) will be queſtioned in this anſwere, but this diſtinction:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> but I ſuppoſe no ſuch thing will bee: becauſe the matter is cleere in it
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:18310:57"/>ſelfe, the name <hi>Sacrament</hi> importeth, that there is this connotation, or relation, over and aboue the vnite, and individuall entitie thereof: for, it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth (at leaſt) that the vnite, and individuall thing is ſacred, and holy; and that is more then the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividuall entity it ſelfe: but howſoever it be with others, this Opponent muſt not oppoſe the latter branch of the diſtinction; for himſelfe doth teach it; expreſſely, if not more fully, then I haue ſet forth: thus he writeth, pag. 47.</p>
               <q>The very being, and nature of the Sacraments, conſiſteth altogether in relation to ſome ſuch gift, and grace ſupernaturall, as God onely can beſtow.</q>
               <p>Theſe things are ſufficient (as I conceiue to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie his firſt argument, in behalfe of Popiſh Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</p>
               <p>His ſecond followeth in this forme.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> 
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>If the Baptiſme in the Romiſh Church bee not true; then it muſt be iterated when they turne to vs.</item>
                  <item>But the Romiſh Baptiſme may not be iterated, when they turne to vs.</item>
                  <item>Therefore the Baptiſme in the Romiſh Church is true Baptiſme.</item>
               </list>
               <p>I anſwere, if by true <hi>Baptiſme</hi> he vnderſtandeth, all things of neceſſitie requyred vnto Baptiſme, then this concluſion ſerues our purpoſe in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent queſtion: for, we inquyre and ſearch after ſuch a Baptiſme, otherwiſe not.</p>
               <p>In that ſence the conſequence of the Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is vnſound,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> and he brings nothing to proue it: wherefore it ſtands refelled, for in this caſe, our
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:18310:57"/>negation is better then his affirmation: he that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth muſt proue, or looſe his action, by the courſe of all courts in the world. Yet (for this time) I will depart from mine owne right, and giue a reaſon for my denyall: becauſe, I deſire to ſatisfie the Reader, and this I ſay:</p>
               <p>Although their Baptiſme want ſome things which of neceſſitie are requyred thereunto, by the inſtitution of Chriſt: yet, from hence will it not follow, that it ought to be repeated: becauſe where Baptiſme is repeated, there all things eſſentiall thereunto (by Chriſts inſtitution) muſt be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: for repetition argues a nullitie. But in the Romiſh Baptiſme, ſome things eſſentiall thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to (by Chriſts inſtitution) are preſent, namely, 1 the water. 2 The words of inſtitution. 3 An outward profeſſion of Chriſtianitie. The firſt and ſecond are eſſentiall to Baptiſme, as it is an individuall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the third is one vſe, and end thereof. So as, thus the caſe ſtands betweene vs: Their Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me is refuſed, becauſe the ſacreed revelation, belei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by a divine faith goes not with it. It is retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, becauſe the water, the words of inſtitution, and the outward profeſſion of Chriſtianitie goes with it: and herein we doe well, becauſe, for want of the firſt, it cannot order vs to heaven: and by the preſence of the reſt, wee follow the inſtitution of Chriſt: when they come vs we cannot giue them of the water, of the words of inſtitution, and of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Chriſtian profeſſion more then they haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready. All that we doe when they come to vs, is, to perfect what is begun, and ſupply what is wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:18310:58"/>
               <p>I anſwere moreover,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> Though I will not deny the Aſſumption, yet if any ſhould, this Opponents proofe could not reſcue it: for, thus he argues: <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, with us, may not bee baptized againe; becauſe, ſuch as former hereticks baptized, were not to be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed againe.</hi> This conſequence (I ſay) is naught, becauſe the Popiſh Church, and former hereticks doe really differ: for <hi>theſe are farre worſe then they,</hi> (as Biſhop <hi>Carleton</hi> hath abundantly proved, in his <hi>Direction to know the true Church</hi>) and here ends my anſwere to his third Argument.</p>
               <p>He concludes this preſent matter more ſolemnly then any other paſſage in this buſineſſe:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I will loſe a little time to ſhew it to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and put my anſwere thereunto. Theſe are his words.</p>
               <q>Our adverſaries, in this cauſe, muſt giue us leaue, till we heare further from them, to thinke this our third Argument, (drawne from the lawfull Baptiſme of the Church of <hi>Rome)</hi> to bee vnanſwerable.</q>
               <p>I anſwere:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> It ſeemeth, when you heare from vs, and finde we ioyne not with you, your minde will change: are you ſo variable, that you are one thing when the ſtreame goes with you, and another when it is againſt you? Well, wee now know your minde, you would not ſay nay, till you had heard vs ſay ſo before you. Now you haue ſo much as you expected, ſee you performe whatſoever you haue promiſed: and ſo I paſſe from this third Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:18310:58"/>
               <head>CHAP. 16. <hi>The fourth Argument for the ſame purpoſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HIs fourth Argument,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> himſelfe ſetteth out in this ſort.
<list>
                     <item>Whereſoever there bee perſons retaining the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteriall function and office, <hi>Epheſ. 4.8.</hi> There is the true Church, becauſe ſuch perſons haue the tutelage of the Church, <hi>Cant. 8.11.</hi> and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Chriſts preſence to the worlds end. <hi>Mat. 28.20.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>But in the Church of Rome there be ſuch perſons.</item>
                     <item>Therefore the Romiſh Church is a true Church.</item>
                  </list> This Argument is implyed in the title of chap. 11. pag. 48. The Propoſition is expreſſely delivered, pag. 50. and the proofe thereof, pag. 49. the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption and the proofe therof is implyed in theſe words:
<q>There is lawfull ordination in the Church of Rome, pag. <hi>56.</hi> In the Church of Rome there is true, and lawfull or dination, wherein they receiue commiſsion, and doe promiſe to teach the people, not the Popes Legends, but out of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: ſo that, both Paſtor and Flock are ours, by admiſsion, promiſe, and ingagement: theirs, by abuſe and practiſe: pag. <hi>58.</hi>
                  </q> The concluſion is alſo implyed in theſe words: <hi>She hath not wholly loſt the face of a Church: pag.</hi> 58.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> I anſwere, a ſhort buſineſſe will ſatisfie this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:18310:59"/>if wee remember what hath beene ſaid touching the two former.</p>
               <p>The propoſition cannot be denied, becauſe where the miniſteriall function (mentioned <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.8.) is preſent, there the word and Sacraments of Chriſt duly adminiſtred connot be wanting, ſeeing this function preſumeth that word, and thoſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments; as a fountaine from whence it flowed, and an obiect whereabout it is exerciſed, as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours words <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19.20. do import.</p>
               <p>But the aſſumption is falſe, and impoſſible to be true. For, they haue forſaken the fountaines of liuing water. <hi>Ier.</hi> 2.13. what life therefore can be in them? Shall we looke for the miniſteriall function, mentioned <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.8. where the words, and ſeales of Chriſts charter are wanting? Surely, no wiſe man will, and he that does, ſhall looſe his longing, and his eyes ſhall ſooner faile, then the thing he lookes for be found. This is enough in the ſtricteſt termes, to refell this argument.</p>
               <p>Yet more ſpecially I anſwere:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> that function <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.8. implyeth a double power the one of <hi>Iuriſdiction,</hi> and the other of <hi>Order.</hi> The firſt doth exerciſe Church diſcipline for goverment; as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of hands vnto ordination, &amp;c. The other adminiſtreth the word and Sacraments, as <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> truly hath it: <hi>De Rom. Pont. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 22. At the begining with the ioynt conſent of all theirs, and ours. Now, neither of theſe powers (of <hi>Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction</hi> or of <hi>Order,</hi> mentioned <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.8.) can be found in the Romiſh Church: for, they ſerue to <hi>gather the Saints,</hi> and to <hi>build vp the body of Chriſt</hi>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:18310:59"/>verſe. 12.13. But the Romiſh Church can haue none ſuch: ſeeing their faith is erronious, and their Sacraments ſhadowes, and without the true ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, ſuch as haue the power of order,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> haue commiſſion <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. to teach divine faith, and adminiſter Chriſts Sacraments, but none amongſt them, haue ſuch commiſſion: for, they are admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and and ordained, <hi>to offer vp the body, and blood of Chriſt, a propitiatory ſacrifice, for the quick and dead,</hi> as we learne by the Councell of Trent. <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 22. <hi>Can.</hi> 1.2.3.</p>
               <p>If any man thinke, that the Councel hath not ſet out the adequate nature of their power of order, he muſt ſhew ſome other Record (conteyning mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of their faith) wherein their order of Preiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood conſiſteth in more then this. But we knowe he cannot: becauſe, perpetuall experience ſhewes, that ſo ſoone as a Preiſt is ordeined, he is ſuch a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificer, and as he is a Preiſt, he doth noe other office, but offer that ſacrifice, what everels they do, it is an addition to their Preiſthood.</p>
               <p>They haue the power of Iuriſdiction in ſome ſort,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> namely ſoe farre as humaine reaſon leads them therevnto. They found that in the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ages of the Church; they ſawe it was comly, and profitable, and therefore they continew it ſtill amongſt them; But, as we ſaid before, of the word and Sacraments, profeſſed and adminniſtred by them; ſo muſt we ſay of power of Iuriſdiction, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to divine faith, they haue no ſuch power: becauſe, they receiue it not from God by his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:18310:60"/>as a Revealer of the ſacred verities: (but, chiefly, and next of all) becauſe, the Paſtors of their Church command it, and accordingly they exerciſe and apply it.</p>
               <p>Theſe things being true, (as they are certaine) The Aſſumption is falſe: for they haue not that power of Iuriſdiction whereof we reade, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.8. for that is ſuch a Iuriſdiction as is received from, and imployed about, the word of divine faith.</p>
               <p>Noreover, this power of Iuriſdiction which we grant them, profits them nothing: becauſe, their power to ordaine Elders, &amp; exerciſe Church Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, ariſing from humane reaſon, and ſerving to humane ends, hath no place, nor power, in conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuting that Church, which is (indeed) the family of Ieſus.</p>
               <p>Now we haue denied his Aſſumption,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven our reaſon for that deniall: we muſt ſee, in the next place, what reaſon he can bring to confirme the ſame: and for that end we find three things: to which I anſwere ioyntly, that they come too ſhort, becauſe they ſerue not to take away the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of our deniall, and therefore are not ſufficient to maintaine his Aſſumption.</p>
               <p>The firſt, himſelfe diſpoſeth thus:
<q>If they haue not lawfull ordination, then haue not we, for ours comes from them.</q>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwere: this comes farre ſhort of his Aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: for in that, he attributes the Miniſteriall fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, (whereof we reade, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.8.) vnto the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church. In this he ſpeakes onely of ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is but one part of that function: ſo as,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:18310:60"/>if he would diſpute from their ordination, as hee does from their Miniſteriall function; his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, would proue their Church to be a true Church, very weakly and lamely: becauſe, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and eſſence of Chriſts Church, is not conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by any power of ordination: and this is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to ſatisfie this conſequence of our Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent <hi>B.</hi> But we will try him a little further.</p>
               <p>Hee ſaith, <hi>Our Ordination came from them,</hi> and thereby he indeavours to proue the foreſaid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence: But it comes ſhort of that: The outward ceremony of Ordination, (that is) the impoſing of hands by one that hath Dioceſan Authority, which we enioy and doe exerciſe, came from them, ſo farre (for this time) we yeeld; that is, that, ſuch Miniſters of ours, as firſt led the way vnto our ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from them, were ordeined or admitted into the worke of the Miniſtery by ſuch authority of theirs. But this proues not, that our Ordination and theirs is the ſame: for, ours ariſeth from, and is exerciſed about, divine faith; ſo is not theirs. Our Ordination, as it ariſeth from, and is exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed about, divine faith, is not received from them: becauſe amongſt them, that divine faith is wholly wanting If then any deſire to know, how they, and we doe agree in the outward ceremony, and diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in the in the inward, and Spirituall life of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion, or the power of Iuriſdiction, left by Chriſt vnto his Church. I anſwere, the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God hath made that difference. They are given vp to beleeue lyes, wee are preſerved in the truth, and faith once delivered to the Saints.</p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:18310:61"/>
               <p>The ſecond proofe of his Aſſumption,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> is contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in theſe words:
<q>Wee doe not ordeine them anew which haue taken Orders from that Sea, when they become con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts.</q>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwere, 1. This proofe hath the ſame fault with the former: Orders cannot argue the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriall function, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.8. becauſe that compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends more then then this, yea, this ſeemes to be but the entrance into the function, and not the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence thereof. 2. I anſwere, The inference is alſo naught. Their ordination may not be repeated when they turne to vs: yet ours and theirs may be eſſentially different, as an empty veſſell may not be reiected, and yet differs from that which is full: and indeed ſoe ſtands the caſe betweene their ordination, and ours. They haue the outward ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony, taken vp by tradition from the precedent and pure ages of the Church: wee haue that and the ſubſtance alſo, becauſe divine faith goes with ours, but is wanting to theirs.</p>
               <p>His third proofe conteineth theſe words.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> 
               </p>
               <q>They receiue commiſsion to teach the Scripture: not the Popes Legends.</q>
               <p>I anſwer, This branch came out of his owne braine. He never found it in any records of their faith. Moreover, the records of their faith are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, as I haue partly alledged, Num. 3. and may further appeare by the 4. Seſſ. of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Trent formerly reported, wherein the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the true ſence of the Scriptures, is attribut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Church, that is, as themſelues expound
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:18310:61"/>it vnto the Pope. If then their preiſts muſt each the Scriptures in the Popes ſenſe, then the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are no better then the Popes Legends, and conſequently when they teach the Scriptures, they teach the Popes Legends.</p>
               <p>To conclude, if Commiſſion to teach the Popes Legends be a Miniſtery differing from the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.8. (as this Opponent implyes) then the Popiſh Prieſthood is not that Miniſtery, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.8, becauſe it teaches the Popes Legends. And thus in ſtead of confirming he overthrowes his Aſſumption.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 17. <hi>The concluſion of the whole, claiming our Opponents promiſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw we haue fully finiſhed the body of the diſputation, we are to come vnto, both our Opponents concluſions, leſt ſomething be left vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touched, to the hurt of the cauſe, and offence to the Reader.</p>
               <p>Our elder Opponent, concludeth his booke, pag. 115. with theſe words.</p>
               <q>I deſire to ſtand, but ſo right as I am in all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Iudgements, I beſeech all Readers to Iudge wiſely, and vprightly of what I haue written.</q>
               <p>And in his ſecond Epiſtle he promiſeth after this ſort.</p>
               <q>If you can ſoundly and ſubſtantially Convince
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:18310:62"/>mee of vntruth, I profeſſe, before God and the world, that, I will yeeld vnto you without any more adoe: being already willing to be overcome of the trueth in this caſe.</q>
               <p>The younger Opponent, pag. 132. ioynes with his partner in the ſame promiſe.</p>
               <q>If I haue erred, I ſhall thank thoſe that will bring mee into the way againe. If I haue favoured any vnſound opinion, yea, or haue ſpoken ſuſpitiou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly, let me ſuffer as an Heretick: but, let no man condemne me till he hath firſt ſhewed me better, and found me obſtinate.</q>
               <p>I anſwere, the whole ſumme of their promiſe, makes vp this conditionall Propoſition.</p>
               <q>If we haue erred we will revoke that errour.</q>
               <p>Whereunto I will adde this Aſſumption.</p>
               <q>But you haue erred.</q>
               <p>And accordingly every muſt make this conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <q>Therefore you muſt revoke your errour.</q>
               <p>The conſequence of the propoſition may not be queſtioned, becauſe then ſelues haue made it, and the one hath <hi>profeſſed (before God)</hi> to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it.</p>
               <p>The other craueth the <hi>punniſhment due to an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritick, if he breakes it.</hi> Wherefore, ſo farr, our ground worke is certaine.</p>
               <p>If they doubt of the aſſumption, they haue offred faire, and I accept it.</p>
               <p>They are content to ſtand to the iudgement of of ſuch readers as be wiſe, honeſt, and do feare God. I deſire noe better arbitratours, They require
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:18310:62"/>to be ſhewed better by ſound, and ſubſtantiall conviction, and I ſay it is the beſt iſſue.</p>
               <p>If therefore, ſuch Readers finde ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction theſe Opponents muſt grant the aſſumption, and execute the concluſion; for every honeſt man performes his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, when he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
